林肯
我们中有人曾服役于堪萨斯第二有色兵团
Some of us was in the Second Kansas Colored.
去年四月在詹金斯渡口抗击叛军(詹金斯渡口战役  1864年4月30日)
We fought the rebs at Jenkins' Ferry last April,
在那之前他们刚刚杀害
just after they've killed
在毒泉被俘的所有黑人士兵(在毒泉战役后针对堪萨斯第一有色兵团的屠杀)
every Negro soldier they captured at Poison Springs.
所以这次在詹金斯渡口
So at Jenkins' Ferry,
我们决定不再生俘叛军
we decided warnt taking no reb prisoners.
而是格杀勿论  不留活口
And we didn't leave a one of'em alive.
我们这些死里逃生的人
The ones of us that didn't die that day,
后来加入了美国116有色兵团
we joined up with the 116th U.S. Colored, sir.
位于肯塔基州纳尔逊营
From Camp Nelson Kentucky.
你叫什么  士兵
What's your name, soldier?
哈罗德・格林列兵  长官
Private Harold Green, sir.
我是艾拉・克拉克下士  长官
I'm Corporal Ira Clark, sir.
马萨诸塞州第五骑兵团
Fifth Massachusetts Cavalry.
我们的人都在那边待命
We're waiting over there.
我们撇下了战马
We're leaving our horses behind,
准备和第24步兵团一起登船
and shipping out with the 24th Infantry
准备下周攻打威尔明顿
for the assault next week on Wilmington.
你们都当兵多久了
How long've you been a soldier?
两年  长官
Two year, sir.
堪萨斯第二有色步兵团
Second Kansas Colored Infantry,
他们在詹金斯渡口作战非常勇猛
they fought bravely at Jenkins' Ferry.
没错  长官
That's right, sir.
他们消灭了上千叛军  长官
They killed a thousand rebel soldiers, sir.
他们英勇无前
They were very brave.
但却比白人士兵每个月少挣3块钱
And making three dollars less each month than white soldiers.
我们第二兵团的小伙子
Us second Kansas boys
除此之外
Another three dollars
还要被克扣3块钱的制服费
subtracted from our pay for our uniforms.
这倒是真事  不过
That was true, yes sir, but.
现在工资倒是一视同仁了
Equal pay now,
但仍然没有黑人被任命为士官
but still no commissioned Negro officers.
我知道  克拉克下士
I am aware of that, Corporal Clark.
您知道再好不过了  长官  但是
Yes, sir, that's good you're aware, sir. It's only that
你觉得威尔明顿之战
Do you think the Wilmington attack
既然白人现在已经习惯于
Now that white people have accustomed themselves
看到黑奴拿起枪为自己而战
to seeing Negro men with guns, fighting on their behalf,
也默许了黑人士兵和自己拿到同样的军饷
and now that they can tolerate Negro soldiers getting equal pay,
也许过不了几年
maybe in a few years
他们就能接受黑人尉官
they can abide the idea of Negro lieutenants and captains.
50年后  或许会有黑人上校
In fifty years, maybe a Negro colonel.
100年后就能参加选举了
In a hundred years, the vote.
战争结束后你会做什么  克拉克下士
What'll you do after the war, Corporal Clark?
去上班  长官  也许您会雇用我
Work, sir. Perhaps you'll hire me.
没准我会的
Perhaps I will.
但是长官
But you should know, sir,
我不想再擦皮鞋了  也不会理发
that I get sick at the smell of bootblack and I cannot cut hair.
我已经有理发师了
I've yet to find a man could cut mine
所以这倒无所谓
so it'd make any difference.
作为一个白人您的头发太卷了
You got springy hair for a white man.
没错  我前任理发师上吊自杀了
Yes, I do. My last barber hanged himself.
他的前任也一样
And the one before that.
还在遗嘱里把剪子留给我
Left me his scissors in his will.
林肯总统  晚上好  小伙子们
- President Lincoln, sir? - Evening, boys.
我们见过您  就在
We saw you at, we
在  在葛底斯堡见过您
- We were at, at - We was at Gettysburg!
你们在葛底斯堡打过仗吗(1863年葛底斯堡战役为南北战争著名战役)
You boys fight at Gettysburg?
没有  我们上个月刚入伍
Naw, we didn't fight there. We just signed up last month.
我们在两年前的公墓演讲见过他(林肯著名的《在葛}斯堡国家烈士公墓落成仪式上的演说》)
We saw him two years ago at the cemetery dedication.
没错  我们听过那次演讲
Yeah, we heard you speak.
我们  唉呀妈呀
We, damn, damn damn!
您到底有多高啊
Hey, how tall are you anyway?!
老天  快闭嘴
Jeez, shut up!
我的演讲你记住了多少
Could you hear what I said?
不太多  长官  那时
No, sir, not much. It was.
先人立国
Four score and seven years ago,
已逾八十有七载
our fathers brought forth on this continent a new nation,
自由平等
conceived in liberty and dedicated to the proposition
乃立国之本
that all men are created equal.
不错  谢谢你
That's good, thank you.
今逢内争
Now we are engaged in a great civil war,
欲明以此
testing whether that nation
为本之国
or any nation so conceived
能永存否
and so dedicated can long endure.
吾人  吾人  吾人来此战场
We are, we are, we are met on a great battlefield of that war?
很好  谢谢
That's good, thank you.
欲以方寸之地
We have come to dedicate a portion of that field
奉我勇士
as a final resting place for those who here gave their lives
勇士者  为赴国难而亡
that that nation might live.
吾人此举
It is
他的叔伯们在战争第二天就牺牲了
His uncles, they died on the second day of fighting.
我还记得最后一段
I know the last part. It is
集合  出发  吾尚存者
- Company up! Move it out! - It is rather
小伙子  该归队了  谢谢你们
Boys, best go and find your company. Thank you.
谢谢您  长官  愿上帝保佑您
Thank you, sir. God bless you.
愿上帝也保佑你
God bless you too.
吾尚存者  当担所余大任
That we here highly resolve
承烈士遗志  倍吾力于未竟之业
that these dead shall not have died in vain.
吾国  神佑之
That this nation, under God,
当获新生之自由
shall have a new birth of freedom,
民有  民治  民享之国
and that government of the people, by the people, for the people,
必永续于世
shall not perish from the earth.
1865年1月
林肯赢得第二次总统选举两个月后
南北战争进入第四个年头
夜深了
It's nighttime.
小船被某种可怕的力量飞速地推动着
The ship's moved by some terrible power, at a terrific speed.
尽管伸手不见五指
Though it's imperceptible in the darkness,
我仍能感觉到我们正向海岸冲去
I have an intuition that we're headed towards a shore.
船上没有其他人
No one else seems to be aboard the vessel and I
我感到一阵强烈的孤独
I'm kinny aware of my aloneness.
若不做那些噩梦(《哈姆雷特》经典独白)
I could be bounded in a nutshell
即使困于核桃壳内
and count myself a king of infinite space
(白宫)
我也可自命为无限疆域之帝王
were it not that I have bad dreams.
我猜我所诧异的是船的速度
I reckon it's the speed that's strange to me,
因为我一直很从容不迫
I'm used to going a deliberate pace.
我应该体谅你  玛丽
I should spare you Mary,
不应该和你讲我的噩梦
I shouldn't tell you my dreams.
我希望能为你分忧
I don't want to be spared if you aren't!
再说你也没体谅过我
And you spare me nothing.
或许这象征着
Perhaps it's
威尔明顿港的战斗
it's the assault on Wilmington port.
你总会在战役之前梦到小船
You dream about the ship before a battle, usually.
头疼怎么样了
How's the coconut?
说不上来
Beyond description.
快两年了  没一点好转
Almost two years, nothing mends.
我也算是战争的受害者
Another casualty of the war.
谁会乐意去听
Who wants to listen to a
一个没用的老婆子抱怨一场车祸呢
useless woman grouse about her carriage accident?
我愿意  拉倒吧
- I do. - Stuff!
你也就跟我讲你的梦  我是给你算命的
You tell me dreams, that's all, I'm your soothsayer.
这就是我对于你的全部意义
That's all I am to you anymore.
我不会再得到你的信任了
I'm not to be trusted,
即便那不是一场简单的车祸
even if it wasn't a carriage accident,
而是一次未遂的暗杀行动
even if it was an attempted assassination.
那次应该不是暗
It was most probably an ass
就是暗杀  而且是针对你的
It was an assassin, whose intended target was you.
宴会准备的怎么样了
How're the plans coming along for the big shindy?
我不想谈宴会的事
I don't want to talk about parties.
你从不在乎宴会
You don't care about parties.
不太在乎  但例行公事也没办法
Not much but they're a necessary hindrance.
我知道了
I know.
我知道小船象征什么了
I know what it's about, the ship.
不是威尔明顿港  不是军事行动
It's not Wilmington Port, it's not a military campaign!
是废奴修正案
It's the amendment to abolish slavery!
否则你怎么会强迫我
Why else would you force
邀请那些激进疯子到家里来
me to invite demented radicals into my home?
你正想办法
You're gonna try to
在任期结束和新就职典礼前
get the amendment passed in the House of Representatives,
让修正案在众议院通过
before the term ends, before the Inauguration.
别在没用的东西上花太多钱
Don't spend too much money on the flub dubs.
没有谁像你一样受人爱戴
No one's loved as much as you,
没有谁像你一样被万人敬仰
no one's ever been loved so much by the people,
你现在可以随心所欲
you might do anything now.
不要把这样的权力
Don't, don't waste that power
浪费在一个注定失败的修正案上
on an amendment bill that's sure to defeat.
你还记得罗伯特也会回来赴宴吗(罗伯特・托德・林肯  林肯长子)
Did you remember Robert's coming home for the reception?
我就知道你会忘
I knew you'd forget.
第13号修正案就是你坐的那条船
That's the ship you're sailing on. The Thirteenth Amendment.
你不说我也知道
You needn't tell me I'm right, I know I am.
这会很晚了  凯克莉夫人(伊丽莎白・凯克莉  前黑奴  后成为裁缝  社会活动家及作家)
Oh it's late, Mrs. Keckley.
夫人需要穿这个参加宴会
She needs this for the grand reception.
这可是精雕细琢的
It's slow work.
晚安
Good night.
你是不是和她讲了你的梦
Did you tell her a dream?
儿童奴隶  12岁  600元
两个男孩  700元
爸爸  怎么了
- Papa? - Hmm?
爸爸  我想见威利
Papa, I wanna see Willie.
我也想  泰迪  但是不可能了
Me too, Taddie. But we can't.
为什么
Why not?
威利不在了  他已经过世3年了(威廉・华莱士・林肯  林肯三子  死于肺炎)
Willie's gone. Three years now. He's gone.
我的任务是来升旗
The part assigned to me is to raise the flag,
如果设备没问题  我会将它升起
which, if there be no fault in the machinery, I will do,
但之后让国旗飘扬的任务就属于人民了
and when up, it will be for the people to keep it up.
演讲结束
That's my speech.
我们不远万里  为国父林肯而战
We are coming Father Abraham three hundred thousand more.
从密州潺潺溪流  到新英巍巍海岸
From Mississipp's winding stream and from New England's shore.
我们弃业从军  无惧妻离子散
We leave our plows and workshops our wives and children dear.
就算众议院的共和党员都投了赞成票
Even if every Republican in the House votes yes,
但这也无法保证
far from guaranteed,
我们党什么时候团结一致过
since when has our party unanimously supported anything?
就假设所有党员都投了赞成票
but say all our fellow Republicans vote for it,
我们仍然会少20票
We'll still be twenty votes short.
才20票吗  才20票
- Only twenty? - Only twenty!
我们会拉到这20票的
We can find twenty votes.
赞成废奴的20名民主党议员
Twenty House Democrats who'll vote to abolish slavery,
在我看来  你的意见总是很宝贵
- In my opinion - To which I always listen.
是奉承话吧  我洗耳恭听呢
- Or pretend to. - With all three of my ears.
我们很快会打赢这场战争
We'll win the war soon.
这是大势所趋  不是吗
It's inevitable, isn't it?
但毕竟还没有赢
Ain't won yet.
你会以一个英雄形象开始下个任期
You'll begin your second term with semi-divine stature.
想象一下和平对我们的意义
Imagine the possibilities peace will bring!
为什么还要让众议院辩论玷污你的光辉形象
Why tarnish your invaluable luster with a battle in the House?
那里鸡飞狗跳
It's a rat's nest in there,
10个月前否决提案的那帮
the same gang of talentless hicks and hacks who
乌合之众乡巴佬还在那里
rejected the amendment ten months ago.
我们输定了
We'll lose.
我觉得现在我们还是有机会的
I like our chances now.
想一想可能面临的困难
Well, consider the obstacles we would face.
我之前说过
The aforementioned
通过一项修正案需要三分之二人的同意
two-thirds majority needed to pass an amendment.
我们争取到了共和党的大多数
We have a Republican majority,
不过也就一半多一点
but barely more than fifty percent.
百分之五十六
Fifty-six.
我们需要民主党的支持
We need Democratic support.
而目前一个都争取不到
There's none to be had.
上次针对修正案的投票以后
Since the House last voted on the amendment,
众议院有过一次选举
there's been an election.
64位民主党员于十一月离开了众议院
Sixty-four Democrats lost their House seats in November,
也就是说三月会新来64名民主党人
that's sixty-four Democrats looking for work come March.
我知道
I know.
他们不用担心改选
They don't need to worry about re-election,
因此他们可以根据自身利益投票
they can vote however it suits'em.
但我们不能收买投票人
But we can't buy the vote for the amendment,
修正案太重要了
it's too important.
我可没提过收买
I said nothing of buying anything.
我只是说还需要20票
We need twenty votes was all I said.
我的下个任期伊始之时
Start of my second term,
可是有不少职位虚位以待呢
plenty of positions to fill.
总统先生  这是乔利夫妇
Mr. President, may I present Mr. And Mrs. Jolly
他们来自密苏里州
who've come from Missouri to
杰佛逊市  总统
From Jeff City, President.
乔利先生  夫人
Mr. Jolly. Ma'am.
壁炉边这位是苏厄德国务卿
This by the fire is Secretary of State Seward.
杰佛逊市
Jeff City.
我听说过一个杰佛逊市的律师
I heard tell once of a Jefferson City lawyer,
养了一只每天早上叫他起床的鹦鹉
who had a parrot that'd wake him each morning,
鹦鹉每天都喊
crying out,
今天就是圣经预言的末日
Today is the day the world shall end as scripture has foretold.
有一天  律师开枪打死了它
And one day, the lawyer shot him
也许是为了耳根清净吧
for the sake of peace and quiet, I presume,
不过至少对于鹦鹉来说  这预言应验了
thus fulfilling, for the bird at least, its prophecy.
杰佛逊市唯一的收费站在西南部
There's only one tollbooth in Jeff City, to the southwest,
自斯科菲尔德将军驻扎当地以来(约翰・斯科菲尔德  时值北军总指挥)
and this man Heinz Sauermagen from Rolla
被一个罗拉市名叫海因茨・苏尔马根的人
been in illegal possession for near two year,
非法占据近两年之久
since your man General Schofield set him up there.
可那地方由门罗总统授予我的祖父(詹姆斯・门罗  美国第五任总统)
But President Monroe give that toll gate to my granpap
昆西・亚当斯也致信过我的父亲(约翰・昆西・亚当斯  美国第六任总统)
and Quincy Adams give my pap a letter
说那里归我们家族所有
saying it's our'n for keeps.
我太太带来了
Mrs. Jolly got the
给林肯先生看看亚当斯总统的信
Show Mr. Lincoln the Quincy Adams letter.
不必了  乔利夫人
That's unnecessary, Mrs. Jolly.
告诉我您的要求好了
Just tell me what you want from me.
我丈夫有肺气肿  不能闻烟味
Mr. Jolly's emphysema don't care for cigars.
夫人  您了解
Madame. Do you know about the
宪法第13号修正案提案吗
proposed Thirteenth Amendment to the Constitution?
是的  先生  所有人都知道
Yes sir, everybody knows of it.
总统赞成这项提案
The President favors it.
你们呢  我们也赞成
- But do you? - We do.
你知道这项法案会废除奴隶制吧
You know that it abolishes slavery?
是的  我知道
Yes sir. I know it.
这是你赞成的原因吗
And is that why you favor it?
我赞成的只是停战
What I favor is ending the war.
我们一废奴  南军就会停战
Once we do away with slavery, the rebs will quit fighting,
因为他们就是为维护奴隶制而战的
since slavery's what they're fighting for.
林肯先生  您总是这样说
Mr. Lincoln, you always say so.
修正案一出台
With the amendment,
奴隶制就会废除  南方叛军也会投降
slavery's ended and they'll give up,
战争也会随之结束
the war can finish then.
假如战争在废奴前就结束  你们还
If the war finished first, before we end slavery, would
林肯总统说除非废奴
President Lincoln says the war won't stop unless
否则战争不会结束
we finish slavery.
我说假如  南军人困马乏
But if it did. The South is exhausted.
假如他们弹尽粮绝
If they run out of bullets and men,
你还会让你们的
would you still want your
你们那里的议员是谁
Who's your representative?
杰佛逊市  是波顿议员吗
Jeff City? That's, Congressman Burton?
瘦竹竿波顿  我是说约西亚・波顿  没错
'Beanpole' Burton. I mean, Josiah Burton, yes.
共和党人
Republican.
相信他还在修正案上摇摆不定
Undecided on the question of the amendment, I believe.
或许你可以去拜见他  告诉他你的热情
Perhaps you could call on him and inform him of your enthusiasm.
好吧  夫人
- Yeah. - Madam?
如果南军下周就投降
If the rebels surrender next week,
你会希望波顿议员
would you, at the end of this month,
在月底对第13号修正案投赞成票吗
want Congressman Burton to vote for the Thirteenth Amendment?
如果战争真的就此结束
If that was how it was, no more war and all,
我想我丈夫
I reckon Mr. Jolly much
会不希望国会通过修正案
prefer not to have Congress pass the amendment.
为什么呢
And, why is that?
因为黑鬼
Niggers.
要是他没有被迫
If he don't have to
让黑鬼们从阿拉巴马跑到密苏里
let some Alabama coon come up to Missouri,
偷了他的鸡  抢了他的工作
steal his chickens and his job,
他大概会支持修正案的
he'd much prefer that.
人民  我似乎开始理解
The people! I begin to see
你为什么要如此迫不及待地推行修正案了
why you're in such a great hurry to put it through.
我可以先看看这封信吗  关于收费站的
Would you let me study this letter, sir, about the tollbooth?
明早再来找我
Come back to me in the morning,
我们会依法处理这件事
and we'll consider what the law says.
别忘了去拜访那位瘦竹竿
And be sure to visit 'beanpole'.
告诉他你们为了结束战争
and tell him that you support passage of the Amendment,
支持修正案
as a military necessity.
谢谢
Thank you.
尼古拉  有空的话
Oh, Nicolay, when you have a moment
如果你打算用职位换取投票
If procuring votes with offers of employment is what you intend,
那我就去找奥尔巴尼的朋友
I'll fetch a friend from Albany
他可以找来
who can supply the skulking men
一些很擅长搞黑幕的人
gifted at this kind of shady work.
免得我劝说民主党时遭到羞辱
Spare me the indignity of actually speaking to Democrats.
你也不用出面担负责任
Spare you the exposure and liability.
失陪一下  我曾郑重起誓
Pardon me, that's a distress signal
绝不对这个敲门声置之不理的
which I am bound by solemn oath to respond to.
汤姆・本德尔把加德纳先生送的
Tom Pendel took away the glass camera plates of slaves
装着黑奴照片的玻璃相框给打碎了
Mr. Gardner sent over
汤姆说妈妈觉得那东西让人看着难受  可
because Tom says mama says they're too distressing, but
你整夜都做噩梦  妈妈这么做是对的
You had nightmares all night, mama's right to
如果你不让我看那些盘子
I'll have worse nightmares,
我会做更多噩梦的
if you don't let me look at the plates again!
也许吧
Perhaps.
我们共和党内承担不起任何闪失
We can't afford a single defection from anyone in our party,
哪怕一位共和党人在投票时缺席也不行
not even a single Republican absent when they vote.
你知道应该找哪些人谈谈
You know who you've got to see.
去找布莱尔家族
Send over to Blair House.
问问普雷斯顿・布莱尔我能否5点去见他一面(普雷斯顿・布莱尔  美国媒体人及政客)
Ask Preston Blair can I call on him around five o'clock.
愿上帝助你一臂之力
God help you.
鬼知道他会向你提出什么要求
God alone knows what he'll ask you to give him.
一旦你们布莱尔家族发话
If the Blairs tell'em to,
就没有共和党人会反对修正案
no Republican will balk at voting for the amendment.
你指的应该是共和党的保守派
No conservative Republican is what you mean.
所有共和党人都应该是保守派
All Republicans ought to be conservative,
我他妈在自己家里建立了这个党
I founded this party in my own goddamned home
希望它成为一个保守的反奴隶制党派
to be a conservative antislavery party,
而不是该死的废奴主义激进派的玩物
not a hobbyhorse for goddamned radical abolitionists.
小声点  爸爸
Damp down the dyspepsia, Daddy!
你会把孩子吓到的
You'll frighten the child.
你需要我们稳定住
You need us to keep
共和党内的保守派
the conservative side of the party in the traces
与此同时你去说服
while you diddle the radicals
并拉拢塞德斯・史蒂文斯那伙激进派(塞德斯・史蒂文斯  共和党激进派领袖)
and bundle up with Thaddeus Stevens' gang,
你需要我们的帮助
You need our help.
是的  没错
Yes, sir, I do.
那我们有什么好处  你也太直接了
- Well, what do we get? - Whoo! Blunt!
礼貌一点儿  蒙蒂
Your manners, Monty.
我算知道为什么林肯先生把你逐出内阁了
Must be why Mr. Lincoln pushed you out of his cabinet.
他不是被逐出的
He was pushed out.
我不是被逐出的  当然不是
- I wasn't pushed. - Oh of course you weren't.
我主动辞职的
I agreed to resign.
他被逐出是为了安抚那些该死的废奴激进派
He was pushed out to placate the goddamn radical abolishonists!
爸爸  请你注意点
Oh Daddy, please! Daddy.
小伙子  你不介意吧
Oh. You don't mind, boy, do you?
他跟士兵一起混过
He spends his days with soldiers.
他们教了我一首歌  是嘛
- They taught me a song! - Did they?
当兵的最会唱歌了
Soldiers know all manner of songs.
你哥哥鲍勃还好吗
How's your brother Bob?
他还在上学
He's at school now,
不过再过4天他就回来参加宴会了
but he's coming to visit in four days. For the shindy!
上学  真棒啊
At school? Ain't that fine!
至少没去参军
Good he's not in the army!
他想去  但是妈妈不让他去
He wants to be, but mama said he can't
当兵危险得很
Dangerous life, soldiering.
你妈妈不让他去很明智
Your mama is wise to keep him clean out of that.
现在你父亲知道我想要什么
Now your Daddy knows that what I want,
换取我对他的帮助
in return for all the help I give him,
如他所承诺的一样  我要去里士满
is to go down to Richmond like he said I could,
萨瓦那一沦陷我就去(萨瓦那  佐治亚州港口城市)
as soon as Savannah fell,
我还要和杰斐逊・戴维斯谈一谈(杰斐逊・戴维斯 南部邦联总统)
and talk to Jefferson Davis.
告诉他我能提供的条件
Give me terms I can offer to Jefferson Davis
以开启和谈
to start negotiating for peace.
他会和我谈的
He'll talk to me!
你们党内的保守派
Conservative members of your party
想让你听一听来自里士满的提议
want you to listen to overtures from Richmond.
这才是重中之重
That above all!
不到别无选择的时候
They'll vote for this rash and dangerous amendment
他们是不会支持这仓促又危险的修正案的
only if every other possibility is exhausted.
共和党人不等于废奴主义者
Our Republicans ain't abolitionists.
我们不能强迫他们支持废奴
We can't tell our people they can vote yes on abolishing slavery
除非我们可以告诉他们
unless at the same time we can tell'em
你这样做是为了停止战争
that you're seeking a negotiated peace.
里奥  到里士满还远着呢
Leo, it's a hundred miles to Richmond.
给他喝点酒让他多睡一会  好的  夫人
- Get him drunk so he can sleep. - Yes ma'am.
爸爸
Here, Daddy.
谢谢  我来帮你铺好
- Oh. Thank you. - Let's fix this up
我帽子呢  在里奥那
- Where's my hat? - Leo has your hat.
好了吗  去争取和平吧
All right? Go make peace.
战神啊  摧枯拉朽地前进吧
Thunder forth, God of War!
我们首先从海上对威尔明顿发起攻击
We'll commence our assault on Wilmington from the sea.
这怎么被烧了
Why is this burnt?
你孩子玩过这个吗
Was the boy playing with it?
几天前被煤灰烧坏了
It got took by breeze several nights back.
这可是陆军部的官方地图
This is an official War Department map!
全内阁都想听听这意味着什么
And the entire cabinet's waiting to hear what it portends.
一场轰炸
A bombardment.
由海军史上最强大的舰队发动的轰炸
From the largest fleet the Navy has ever assembled.
白首海皇  吾将撼汝
Old Neptune, shake thy hoary locks!
58艘战舰已经在射程内抛锚
Fifty-eight ships are underway
随时准备行动
of every tonnage and firing range.
我们将组成长时间的火力网
We'll keep up a steady barrage.
第一个目标是非瑟堡
Our first target is Fort Fisher.
它是威尔明顿港的要冲之地
It defends Wilmington Port.
长时间的火力网
A steady barrage?
每分钟100发炮弹
A hundred shells a minute.
打到他们投降为止
Till they surrender.
老天  可不是
- Dear God. - Yes, yes.
威尔明顿是他们最后的港口  也就是说
Wilmington's their last open seaport. Therefore
拿下威尔明顿  里士满也手到擒来
Wilmington falls, Richmond falls after.
战争也将随之结束
And the war is done.
恕我冒昧  那为什么
Then why, if I may ask,
公众的视线没有聚焦在威尔明顿
are we not concentrating the nation's attention on Wilmington?
为什么《先驱报》报道的却是
Why, instead, are we reading in the Herald,
我们在促使废奴主义修正案
that the anti-slavery amendment is being precipitated
提交众议院进行辩论呢
onto the House floor for debate?
你急切的愿望
Because your eagerness,
在我看来就是行政权
in what seems an unwarranted intrusion of the Executive
对立法权的无理干涉
into Legislative prerogatives,
它很可能会
is compelling it to it's
让你的计划胎死腹中
to what's likely to be its premature demise.
听到了吗
You hear?
《解放黑人奴奴宣言》已经颁布了(1862年9月22日颁布)
You signed the Emancipation Proclamation,
你应该心满意足了
You're done all that can be expected.
《解放黑人奴奴宣言》只不过是个战时措施
The Emancipation Proclamation merely a war measure.
战争一结束法院就会拿它小题大做的
After the war the courts will make a meal of it.
爱德华・贝茨当司法部长的时候
When Edward Bates was Attorney General,
对这个宣言可是信心满满的
he felt confident in it enough to allow you to sign.
每个律师都有他自己的想法
Different lawyers, different opinions.
宣言只是武装解放黑奴  并没有在其它
It frees slaves as a military exigent, not in any other
我不记得爱德华・贝茨对于
I don't recall Edward Bates being any too certain
宣言的合法性有多么肯定
about the legality of my Proclamation
它只不过是不非法而已
just it wasn't downright criminal.
还处于一个灰色地带
Somewhere's in between.
我还在伊利诺伊州当律师的时候
Back when I rode the legal circuit in Illinois,
我曾为一个来自梅塔莫拉市的老妇辩护
I defended a woman from Metamora named
她叫梅丽莎・格英丝  当时已77岁了
Melissa Goings, 77 years old.
她被指控杀害了她83岁的丈夫
They said she murdered her husband, he was 83.
他丈夫想掐死她
He was choking her,
于是这个女人抓起一根柴火
and she grabbed a hold of a stick of fire wood
打碎了他的脑袋  杀死了他
and fractured his skull, and he died.
她丈夫在遗嘱里写到
In his will he wrote:
我希望她真把我打死了
I expect she has killed me.
否则  我一定会报仇的
If I get over it, I will have revenge.
大家看到她的丈夫是这个德行
No one was keen to see her convicted,
都不想判她有罪
he was that kind of husband.
我征求了起诉律师的意见
I asked the prosecuting attorney
和她短短的见了一面
if I might have a short conference with my client.
我们约在法院的一个房间见面
And she and I went into a room in the courthouse,
但她没有出现
but I alone emerged.
屋里的窗户大开着
The window in the room was found to be wide open,
人们相信她是跳窗自杀了
It was believed the old lady may have climbed out of it.
我告诉法庭监守
I told the bailiff
就在我离开房间之前
Right before I left her in the room,
她问我她哪有好喝的水
she asked me where she could get a good drink of water,
我回答她田纳西州有
and I told her Tennessee.
格英丝夫人再也没有出现在梅塔莫拉
Mrs. Goings was seen no more in Metamora.
正义得到了伸张
Enough justice had been done.
甚至没人向担保人要保释金
They even forgave the bondsman her bail.
我恐怕不太  我断定
- I'm afraid I don't see - I decided
宪法赋予我开战的权力
that the Constitution gives me war powers,
可没人知道那究竟是何种权力
but no one knows just exactly what those powers are.
有人说它不存在  我不知道  我坚信
Some say they don't exist. I don't know. I decided,
我需要它们的存在
I needed them to exist to
以坚守我保护宪法的誓言
uphold my oath to protect the Constitution,
所以我决定
which I decided meant that
我可以把反叛者的奴隶
I could take the rebels' slaves from 'em as
作为战时财产没收充公
property confiscated in war.
这的确可能让人怀疑我与南军看法相同
That might recommend to suspicion that I agree with the rebs
怀疑我从一开始就认为
that their slaves are
奴隶是财产  但我当然不那么认为
property in the first place. Of course I don't.
我从不那样认为  任何人获得自由都令我高兴
I never have, I'm glad to see any man free,
况且若把人视乎财产或战时禁运品
and if calling a man property, or war contraband
即能解放黑奴  我又何苦大费周章
does the trick, why I caught at the opportunity.
棘手的地方是
Now here's where it gets truly slippery.
我应用法律准许战争中没收财产
I use the law allowing for the seizure of property
因为知道
in a war knowing it applies
它仅适用于好战国的政府财产和公民
only to the property of governments and citizens of belligerent nations.
但南方不是一个国家
But the South ain't a nation.
因此我无法跟他们谈判
That's why I can't negotiate with 'em.
那要是我坚称他们只是叛民
So if in fact the Negroes are property according to law,
并非好战国公民
have I the right to take the rebels' property from 'em,
法律规定黑人确实是财产
if I insist they're rebels only,
我有权把他们没收回来吗
and not citizens of a belligerent country?
更麻烦的是
And slipperier still: I maintain
我坚持认为并非我国南方叛乱
that it ain't our actual Southern states in rebellion,
只是因为叛民居于南方
but only the rebels living in those states,
而南方依法为战时状态
the laws of which states remain in force.
依法为战时状态
The laws of which states remain in force.
即是说既然是由宪法决定
That means, that since it's states' laws that determine
黑人能否作为奴隶或财产买卖
whether Negroes can be sold as slaves, as property,
联邦政府不能予以干涉
the Federal government doesn't have a say in that,
起码至今还不能
at least not yet,
那些州的奴隶因此便是财产
then Negroes in those states are slaves, hence property, hence
因此我的开战权让我得以
my war powers allow me to
如此执行没收  我就这么做了
confiscate 'em as such, so I confiscated 'em.
但如若我是一名尊崇宪法的人
But if I'm a respecter of states' laws,
除了作废宪法之外
how then can I legally free 'em with my Proclamation as I done,
我又如何能合法地以宣言解放他们
unless I'm cancelling states' laws?
我认为内战需要我这么做
I felt the war demanded it.
我的职责迫使我这么做
my oath demanded it,
我认为这是正确的  希望能合法达到这一目的
I felt right with myself, and I hoped it was legal to do it
至今都希望如此
I'm hoping stilll.
两年前我正式宣布解放他们
Two years ago I proclaimed these people emancipated,
那么从此永远地解放了
Then, thenceforward and forever free.
但法庭判决我无此权力
But let's say the courts decide I had no authority to do it.
也许他们做出了正确的裁决
They might well decide that.
假设并未修订废奴修正案
Say there's no amendment abolishing slavery.
假设战后
Say it's after the war,
我将不能再通过
and I can no longer use my
有时不得不使用的开战权
war powers to just ignore the courts' decisions,
忽视法庭判决
like I sometimes felt I had to do.
那么我解放的人民会被重新奴役吗
Might those people I freed be ordered back into slavery?
因此我想要众议院
That's why I'd like to get
通过第13号修正案
the Thirteenth Amendment through the House,
借此得到国家的认可
and on its way to ratification by the states,
一劳永逸
wrap the whole slavery thing up,
尽我所能地解决奴隶制的余孽
forever and aye, as soon as I'm able.
本月末  我想要你们对我做出支持
Now! End of this month! And I'd like you to stand behind me,
做出内阁应有的支持
like my cabinet's most always done.
牧师说  我可以少些布道言说
As the preacher said, I could write shorter sermons but
但我一提笔  就无法停下
once I start I get too lazy to stop.
依我看  先生  您这正是
It seems to me, sir, you're describing precisely
民主党所言的独裁者形象
the sort of dictator the Democrats have been howling about.
独裁者向来无视法律
Dictators aren't susceptible to law.
他也如此  他宣扬正是独裁之举
Neither is he! He just said as much!
无视法院  曲解道义  如此
Ignoring the courts, twisting meanings, what
如此慷慨激昂  那么
- what reins him in from, from  - Well,
我想人人都会有激动的时刻
the people do that, I suppose.
一年半前  在第二次竞选前
I signed the Emancipation Proclamation a year and half,
我签署了《解放黑人奴隶宣言》
before my second election,
我自认有权签署
I felt I was within my power to do it.
然而我也知道我或许有错
However I also felt that I might be wrong about that.
我早知人们会那么说
I knew the people would tell me,
就给了他们一年半的时间考虑
I gave 'em a year and half
而他们再次选择了我
to think about it, and they reelected me.
一到二月的首要之事
And come February the first,
便是我要签署第13号修正案
I intend to sign the Thirteenth Amendment.
阿什利代表先生
Well, Mr. Representative Ashley!
国会山那有什么新闻(美国国会的办公大楼  建在一海拔83英尺高地上  故名国会山)
Tell us the news from the Hill.
新闻
Ah! Well, news
为何如此突然
Why for instance is this thus,
这其中又有何缘由
and what is the reason for this thusness?
詹姆斯  我们想由你
James, we want you to bring the
在众议院中提议反奴修正案
anti-slavery amendment to the floor for debate.
不好意思  您说什么  即刻提出
- Excuse me, what? - Immediately.
您负责管理修正案  对吧
You are the amendment's manager, are you not?
是没错  但
I am, of course, but
我们还要指望激进分子的支持
And we're counting on robust radical support,
所以通知史蒂文斯先生一声
so tell Mr. Stevens
我们期待他的支持  此事会很艰难
we expect him to put his back into it. It's not going to be easy,
但我们相信  不可能
- but we trust - It't impossible.
不行  抱歉  我们无法
No, I am sorry, no, we can't
立刻在众议院组织任何事宜
organize anything immediately in the House.
从选举起我就一直在游说民主党员
I have been canvassing the Democrats since the election,
以防他们被击败后一蹶不振
in case any of them softened after they got walloped.
但他们的态度进来日益强硬  国务卿先生
But they have stiffened if anything, Mr. Secretary,
选票还不够
there aren't nearly enough votes
我们是捕鲸者  阿什利先生
We're whalers, Mr. Ashley!
捕鲸者  抓鲸鱼的吗
Whalers? As in, um whales?
我们追杀这条鲸鱼很久了
We're been chasing this whale for a long time.
我们最后向这怪物背上刺入了鱼叉
We're finally placed a harpoon in the monster's back.
开战了  詹姆斯  开战了
It's in, James, it's in!
我们履行了契约  时不可待
We finish the deed now, we can't wait!
否则他一旦反身而动
Or with one flop of his tail,
就会使我们的努力付之一炬
he'll smash the boat and send us all to eternity.
今年本月31日
On the 31st of this month. Of this year.
让众议院就修正案投票
Put the amendment up for a vote.
捕鲸者
Whalers?
他这么说的
That's what he said.
他这辈子从未上过捕鲸船
The man's never been near a whale ship in his life!
撤回激进分子的支持
Withdraw radical support,
逼他放弃他的野心
force him to abandon this scheme, whatever he's up to.
他做事总拖泥带水
He-He He drags his feet about everything,
林肯  为何这次如此心急
Lincoln. Why this urgency?
我们人多  可以不费力地
We got it through the Senate
让参议院通过了此事
without difficulty because we had the numbers.
这样12月众议院也会同样通过
Come December you'll have the same in the House.
修正案会轻松通过
The amendment'll be the easy work of ten minutes.
他在以修正案胁迫
He's using the threat of the amendment
反叛者立刻投降
to frighten the rebels into an immediate surrender.
我想我们会很高兴看到那一幕的
I imagine we'd rejoice to see that.
就算我们通过了
Will you rejoice, when the
等南方各州遂了林肯的意
Southern states have re-joined the Union pell-mell as
重新加入联邦的乱局
Lincoln intends them to,
依次拒批修正案的话  你会开心吗
and one by one each refuses to ratify the amendment?
因此我们不会通过
If we pass it, which we won't.
我们为什么要同他合作
Why are we co-operating with-with him?
我们都知道他在做什么  他会做什么
We all know what he's doing, and we all know what he'll do.
我们不能顺应
We can't offer up abolition's
最想合法废奴的人的手腕
best legal prayer to his games and tricks.
他说过他会
He's said he'd welcome the
以被囚的奴隶迎接南军
South back with all its slaves in chains.
三年前他那么说  以平息
Three years ago he said that. To calm the border states
各州  我不知道
- when we were - I don't.
你刚说
You said
我们知道他要做什么  但我不知道
we all know what he'll do. I don't know.
你知道他不可信  信任吗
- You know he isn't to be trusted. - Trust? Oh
抱歉  我还以为
I'm sorry, I was under the
你是政治家呢
misapprehension your chosen profession was politics.
我未曾信任过总统  或是任何人
I've never trusted the President. I never trust anyone.
但他没有让你惊讶吗
But hasn't he surprised you?
没有  史蒂文斯先生  一点也没有
No, Mr. Stevens, he hasn't.
什么也震惊不了你  阿萨
Nothing surprises you, Asa.
所以对你而言不存在惊讶
Therefore nothing about you is surprising.
也许这就是为何
Perhaps that is why your
您没有再次当选
constituents did not re-elect you to the coming term.
太迟了  我老了  我要回家
It's late, I'm old, I'm going home.
林肯成日游手好闲  是南方人
Lincoln the inveterate dawdler, Lincoln the Southerner,
是屈从的妥协者
Lincoln the capitulating compromiser,
是我们的敌人  也是
our adversary and.
被上帝遗弃的共和党  我党的领袖
leader of the god forsaken Republican Party, our party.
亚伯拉罕・林肯要求我们
Abraham Lincoln has asked us to work with him
与他一起废除美国的奴隶制
to accomplish the death of slavery in America.
即便反对
Retain, even in opposition,
也要保持你们讶异的能力
your capacity for astonishment.
谁都不许提起总统
The President is never to be mentioned.
也不许提起我  不注意的话就等着喝西北风吧
Nor I. You're paid for your discretion.
不过  不给钱我就不能保证
Hell, you can have that for nothin'.
我们要钱是为了贿赂选票
What we need money for is bribes.
钱能通神
It'd speed things up.
不  任何事都必须合法
No. Nothing strictly illegal.
贿赂议员的确不合法
It's not illegal to bribe Congressmen.
但不受贿他们就会饿死
They starve otherwise.
我跟比尔博先生和莱瑟姆先生解释了
I have explained to Mr. Bilbo and Mr. Latham
我们为投赞成票的民主党人提供工作
that we're offering patronage jobs to the Dems who vote yes.
只提供工作  仅此而已  没错
- Jobs and nothing more. - That's correct.
议员真不值钱
Congressmen come cheap!
几千块就搞定了
Few thousand bucks'll buy you all you need.
你这么说  总统会不高兴的
The President would be unhappy to hear you did that.
那我们输了的话他会高兴吗
Well, will he be unhappy if we lose?
先生们  我付的钱只能用在
The money I managed to raise for this endeavor
你们的衣食住行花销上
is only for your fees, your food, and lodgings, sir.
要是那个松鼠猖獗
If that squirrel-infested
四个人挤在一起的阁楼算宿舍的话
attic you've quartered us in's any measure,
你这费用还真吃紧
you ain't raised much.
可以开工了吗
Shall we get to work?
众议院有请费尔南多・伍德
The House recognizes Fernando Wood,
众议院辩论开始
1月9日
尊敬的代表来自纽约
the honorable representative from New York.
尊敬的各位同僚
Estimable colleagues.
两年前的本月
Two bloody years ago this month,
亚伯拉罕古猿国王一世
his Highness King Abraham Africanus the First,
我们的伟大篡权暴君
our Great Usurping Caesar,
破坏人身保护权和言论自由权之徒
violator of habeas corpus and freedom of the press,
滥用宪法赋予州的权利之人
abuser of states' rights
若林肯真是暴君  伍德先生
If Lincoln really were a tyrant, Mr. Wood,
他早就会把你的空脑壳钉穿了
he'd'a had your empty head impaled on a pike!
这样对我们的国家也好
And the country better for it!
你们这些激进的共和独裁者
Your radical republican autocrat
受制于法令和戒严令
ruling by fiat and martial law,
给他的名字贴上罪恶而违法的
affixed his name to his on a
黑奴解放宣言标签
heinous and illicit Emancipation Proclamation,
保证宣言会加速结束内战
promising it would hasten the end of the war,
然而战火依旧  熊熊燃烧
which yet rages on and on.
他如暴君般声称
He claimed, as tyrants do,
战事的紧急准许他把我们的部队
that the war's emergencies permitted him to turn our army
纽约代表团看起来完全不为所动啊
The New York delegation's looking decidedly uninspired.
激进共和主义即是盲从废奴主义
and radical Republicanism's abolitionist fanaticism!
他的《解放黑人奴隶宣言》
His Emancipation
将千百万美金付之一炬
Proclamation has obliterated millions of dollars
宾夕法尼亚那边
Over in Pennsylvania
慌张的啃手指的人是谁
who's the sweaty man eating his thumb?
我不清楚  看起来快吓尿裤子了
Unknown to me. Seems jumpy.
说不定他真会尿出来
Perhaps he'll jump.
但这一切对这名独裁者来说远远不够
But all that was not enough for this dictator,
现如今他还要暗示
who now seeks to insinuate
老天
Jesus!
这个冒失的混球什么时候能坐下
When's this son-of liberty sonofabitch gonna sit down?
他再不停  约翰・埃利斯就要把表弄坏了
John Ellis is going to break his watch if he doesn't stop.
他再一次要求大家
We are once again asked
不对  是强迫大家考虑第13号修正案的提议
Nay, commanded to consider a proposed thirteenth amendment.
若此案通过  就等于即刻释放了
Which, if passed, shall set at immediate liberty
四百万有色人种
four million coloreds while
同时束缚了美国白人
manacling the limbs of the white race in America
但那只是假设  我们不会让它通过
If it is passed. But it shall not pass!
更有趣的是
What's more interesting is
伊曼先生似乎十分阴沉不快
how dismal and disgruntled Mr. Yeaman appears.
每一位众议院成员
Every member of this House.
他该欢呼的  可是
He should be cheering right now, but
他像吃坏肚子了
Looks like he ate a bad oyster.
各位都该反对
and the constituents which it serves shall oppose!
可以插一句吗  议长先生
A point of order, Mr. Speaker, if you please?
议长先生  我还没讲完
Mr. Speaker, I still have the floor,
而宾夕法尼亚来的先生
and the gentleman from Pennsylvania
却要捣乱  伍德先生何时
- is out of order! - When will Mr. Wood
才能结束这冗长不休的讲演呢
conclude his interminable gabble?
有些人需要呼吸氧气
Some of us breathe oxygen,
而我们在他的讲说中发现
and we find the mephitic fumes of his oratory
对我们肺部有致命威胁的恶臭
a lethal challenge to our pulmonary capacities.
我们该反对修订案
We shall oppose this amendment,
以及任何冒犯自然法则
and any legislation that so affronts natural law,
和侮辱人神的法令
insulting to God as to man!
国会定不能忤逆上帝
Congress must never
宣布他所创造的不同可以等同
declare equal those whom God created unequal!
奴隶制才是对自然法则唯一的侮辱
Slavery is the only insult to natural law,
你这愚昧的蠢材
you fatuous nincompoop!
保持秩序
Ordeeer!
注意程序  议长先生  伍德先生在发言
Procedure! Mr. Speaker, Mr. Wood has the floor!
教教我们  伟大的平民
Instruct us, Oh Great Commoner,
你认为什么才是忤逆自然的
what is unnatural, in your opinion?
黑鬼参与投票吗
Niggrahs casting ballots?
黑鬼代表吗  这些就不忤逆自然了吗  史蒂文斯
Niggrah representatives, is that natural, Stevens?
异族通婚吗
Intermarriage?
亵渎了自然法规的是奴隶制
What violates natural law, slavery,
还有你  彭德尔顿  你侮辱上帝
and you, Pendleton, you insult God!
你这个忤逆自然的杂音
You unnatural noise.
克法克斯先生  请维持秩序
Mr. Coffax, please, use your gavel.
你在捣乱  注意会议秩序
- You are out of order! - Order in the Chamber!
让警卫官压制混乱
Instruct the sergeant of arms to suppress this!
这是在庭上
We are in session!
请不要助长混乱
Please don't encourage this!
千万不要
Don't encourage this!
你回来了  你回来了  你回来了
You're back, you're back, you're back, you're back!
我回来了  你的羊长大了
I am. Your goat got big.
来  帮我搬回房间
Here, help me get one of these to my room.
她在吗
Is she in there?
她大概在睡觉
She's asleep, probably.
要帮忙吗  先生  我可以
You need help, sir? I can
不用了  先生  不用
No, sir, I don't. No.
我可以帮你  不用了
- I can - No.
能帮我把我的
Could you bring your pa this
破产程序令状信交给您父亲吗
letter I writ about my insolvency proceedings?
你自己送你的破产请愿书
You deliver your own goddamned petition
因为有本
'cause there's a new
山姆・贝克威思的雀科相关的新书
book that Sam Beckwith says is about finches,
还有关于鸟喙和他们如何
and finches' beaks, about how they
他来了  卡斯伯特夫人  他来了
He's here, Mrs. Cuthbert! He's here!
罗比  妈妈
- Robbie - Hi, ma.
罗比
Oh, Robbie
Robbie. Oh!
什么
What?
你就待几天  怎么带了这么多东西
You're only staying a few days. Why'd you pack all of that?
我不知道要待多久
Well, I don't know how long I'm
去告诉你父亲罗伯特回家了
Go tell your father Robert's home!
尼古拉先生说爸爸在单独会见布莱尔先生
Mr. Nicolay says daddy's secluded with Mr. Blair.
那也告诉他一声
Tell him anyway.
你跟他一样不好好吃饭  没有
- You forget to eat, exactly like him. - No
接待会之后  返校前
You'll linger a few days extra,
你再待几天
after the reception, before you go back to school.
不知道我还会不会回学校
Well, I don't know if I'm gonna go back to s
你回波士顿之前我们要把你喂胖点
We'll fatten you up before you return to Boston.
好的  妈妈  好的
- All right, mama. - All right.
罗比
Oh Robbie
杰斐逊・戴维斯派来三名代表
Jefferson Davis is sending three delegates:
史蒂芬斯  亨特和坎贝尔
Stephens, Hunter and Campbell.
南部邦联的副总统
Vice President of the Confederacy,
他们的前国务卿
their former Secretary of State,
以及他们的陆军助理部长
and their Assistant Secretary of War.
郑重前来进行和平谈判
They're coming in earnest to propose peace.
我知道这对你来说是不好的消息
I know this is unwelcome news for you.
现在听我说
Now hear me.
我去里士满见卖国贼
I went to Richmond to talk to traitors,
跟他们谈话赔笑  还恳求他们
to smile at and plead with traitors,
因为还有两个月就到春天了
because it'll be spring in two months,
道路就可以通行了  春季屠杀就会开始
the roads'll be passable, the Spring slaughter commences.
过去四个春天了
Four bloody Springs now!
想想你深埋心底的我的弗兰克
Think of my Frank, who you've taken to your heart,
想想内战夺走了数以万计的孩子性命
how you'll blame yourself if the war takes my son
你会如何怪责自己
as it's taken multitudes of sons.
想想不和解还将有多少孩子死去
Think of all the boys who'll die if you don't make peace.
你必须跟这些人谈谈
You must talk with these men!
我想谈  普雷斯顿
I intend to, Preston.
作为回报  我得要求  不  没有讨价还价的余地
- And in return, I must ask you - No, this is not horsetrading,
这事关性命  闲人勿扰
- this is life! -  NOT NOW!
鲍勃  对不起
Bob. I'm sorry.
欢迎回家  谢谢
- Welcome home. - Thank you.
你看着不错  罗伯特  看来你挺适应在哈佛的生活
You're looking fit, Robert. Harvard agrees with you.
布莱尔先生  普雷斯顿  孩子
- Mr. Blair. - Preston, son.
请等我们一会  罗伯特  谢谢
If you just give us a moment please, Robert. Thank you.
我会信守承诺帮您拉票  先生
I will procure your votes for you, as I promised, sir.
您一直都言出必行
You're always kept your word to me.
现在南方人来了
Those Southern men are coming.
我以父之名恳求您  先生
I beg you, in the name of Gentle Christ, sir.
我理解
I understand.
跟他们和平谈判吧
Talk peace with these men.
我理解  普雷斯顿
I understand, Preston.
目前有一票弃权
We have one abstention so far.
雅各・格瑞勒
Jacob Graylor.
他想当宾夕法尼亚的
He'd like to be Federal Revenue
第五区联邦收益估价员
Assessor for the Fifth District of Pennsylvania.
那么从今天起
So the total of representatives
代表投票总数减少到182票
voting three weeks from today is reduced to 182,
因此众议院所需的
which means 122 yes votes
三分之二就是122票赞成
to reach the requisite two thirds of the House.
假设有民主党人投票给修正案
Assuming all Republicans vote for the amendment.
那去除弃权票
Then, despite our abstention,
还差20票赞成才能达到三分之二
to reach a two-thirds majority we remain 20 yeses short.
我们要从64名
For which we're
即将卸任的民主党员官员争取来
seeking from among 64 lame duck Democrats.
这其中有39人无法劝服
Fully 39 of these we deem unredeemable no votes.
他们憎恶黑人
The kind that hates niggers,
憎恨上帝创造了黑人
hates God for making niggers.
上天会对他们的灵魂失望的
The Good Lord on High would despair of their souls.
感谢你的简短解释  比尔博先生
Thank you for that pithy explanation, Mr. Bilbo.
我们已经抛弃这39名被邪恶附身的灵魂
We've abandoned these 39 to the Devil that possesses them.
我们一直在动员
The remaining lame ducks,
其他即将卸职的官员
on whom we've been working with a purpose.
查尔斯・汉森
Charles Hanson.
盖尔斯・斯图亚特
Giles Stuart.
尼尔森・米瑞克
Nelson Merrick.
荷马・班森
Homer Benson.
班森
最后还有
And lastly
俄亥俄的克莱・霍金斯
Clay Hawkins. Of Ohio.
他是西部保留地的收税员
T-tax collector for the Western Reserve, it
收入颇丰
Th-that pays handsomely.
不要只盯着高层
Don't just reach for the highest branches,
他们是墙头草
they sway in every breeze.
要我看  马尔斯顿的助理港口稽查员  有戏
Assistant Port Inspector of Marlston looks like the ticket to me.
船让我恶心
Uh, boats, they-they make me sick.
那就站在码头上
So just stand on the dock.
让助理港口稽查员饿饿肚子
Let the Assistant Assistant Port Inspector's stomach go weak.
最后  民主党员第六张赞成票  俄亥俄的霍金斯
And lastly, Democratic yes vote number six. Hawkins from Ohio.
六票  目前是
- Six. - Well, thus far.
加上格瑞勒的弃权票
Plus Graylor's abstention.
积少成多  霍金斯得了什么位子
- From tiny acorns and so on. - What'd Hawkins get?
米勒斯堡邮政局的所长
Postmaster of the Millersburg Post Office.
他还挺好收买的  是吧
He's selling himself cheap, ain't he?
没错  一个初当议员  搞不定改选的人
Aye, he wanted tax collector of the Western Reserve,
想当西部保留地的收税员
a first-term congressman who couldn't manage reelection,
我觉得不合适  他们把价压到所长
I felt it unseemly and they bargained him down to Postmaster.
把任命分散进行
Scatter 'em over several
以免引人注意
rounds of appointments, so no one notices,
事成后请烧掉账目
and burn this ledger, please, after you're done.
到了我的共和观点受洗之时了
Time for my public opinion bath.
不然让他们也加入吧
Might as well let 'em in.
埃利斯先生的7票  还差13票
Seven yeses with Mr. Ellis. Thirteen to go.
最后一项  一个荒谬但
One last item, an absurdity, but
我的伙伴说代表中
My associates report that among the Representatives,
流传着一个奇异的传闻
a fantastical rumor's bruited about,
你让老眼昏花的普雷斯顿・布莱尔
which I immediately disavowed,
去里士满邀请杰夫・戴维斯
that you'd allowed bleary
派行政长官
old Preston Blair to sojourn to Richmond
到华盛顿来和平谈判
to invite Jeff Davis to send
我即刻否认了
commissioners up to Washington with a peace plan.
我自然跟他们说你绝不会那么做
I, of course, told them you would never..
没询问我  你不会那么做的
Not without consulting me, you wouldn't
因为你又究竟为何那么做呢
Because why on earth would you?
不胜感激
Much obliged.
你为何不咨询我的意见  我可是国务卿
Why wasn't I consulted?! I'm Secretary of State!
你非正式地派出一个反动的老糊涂过去
You You-you informally send a reactionary dottard to
等特使团抵达后
What will happen, do you imagine,
你想象过会如何吗
when these peace commissioners arrive?
我们会听听他们的要求  太妙了
- We'll hear 'em out. - Oh, splendid!
然后民主党员
And next the Democrats
会请他们
will invite 'em up to hearings on the Hill,
和新闻媒体到国会山参加听证会
and the newspapers, well, the newspapers
媒体还会询问
the newspapers will ask
既然他们是来求和的  为何在奴隶制的问题上
why risk enraging the Confederacy over the issue of slavery
冒激怒南部邦联的险
when they're here to make peace?
不止保守派共和党人会加入他们
We'll lose every Democrat we've got,
我们还会失去已有民主党员的支持
more than likely conservative
而我们所有的努力
Republicans will join 'em, and all our work,
一切赢得投票的基础
all our preparing the ground for the vote,
至此烟消云散
laid waste, for naught.
如果我们听取这些人的话
The Blairs have promised support
布莱尔家族答应会支持修正案
for the amendment if we listen to these people.
布莱尔家族答应了吗
Oh, the Blairs promise, do they?
那些代表的要求
You think they'll keep their
一定是保留奴隶制
promise once we have heard these delegates
而你还指望
and refused them? Which we will have to do,
我们拒绝这些代表的要求后
since their proposal most
他们还信守承诺吗
certainly will be predicated on keeping their slaves!
如果走漏了风声说我拒绝停战
What hope for any Democratic votes, William,
那民主党的选票会怎么样  威廉
if word gets out that I've refused a chance to end the war?
你认为世上有不透风的墙吗  华盛顿会有吗
You think word won't get out? In Washington?
要么通过这个修正案  要么停战
It's either the amendment or this Confederate peace,
鱼和熊掌不可兼得
you cannot have both.
你若能窥视时间的种子
If you can look into the seeds of time,
能预知哪一颗能长出金黄的稻麦
and say which grain will grow and which will not,
那么对我说
speak then to me
灾难  这真是场灾难
Oh, disaster. This is a disaster!
时间会说明一切的  威廉
Time is a great thickener of things, William.
是啊  我也觉得
Yes, I suppose it is.
我都不知道你说这些干什么
Actually I have no idea what you mean by that.
给我弄13张赞成票
Get me thirteen votes.
里士满的家伙还没到呢
Them fellers from Richmond ain't here yet.
美军总部  弗吉尼亚州  1月12日
你在波士顿征了一半的人当兵
You drafted half the men in Boston!
他们的家人会怎么看待我
What do you think their families think about me?
他们没有对我扔东西吐口水
The only reason they don't throw things and spit on me
只是因为你受人爱戴
is 'cause you're so popular.
我无法专心学习英国商业法
I can't concentrate on British mercantile law,
我不关心什么英国商业法
I don't care about British mercantile law.
我都不想成为律师
I might not even want to be a lawyer.
这是个铁饭碗
It's a sturdy profession,
还能让你成为有用之人
and a useful one.
我现在就想成为有用的人  不是等以后
Yes, and I want to be useful, but now, not afterwards!
我可不戴这个  斯莱德先生
I ain't wearing them things, Mr. Slade,
他们从来不搭
they never fit right.
太太想让你戴上它们  别想丢下它
The Mrs. will have you wear 'em. Don't think about leaving 'em.
你在推脱  这是你最喜欢的手段
You're delaying, that's your favorite tactic.
你嘴上不说
You won't tell me no,
但是战争一个月内就会结束  你知道的
but the war will be over in a month, and you know it will!
我觉得预言本身
I've found that prophesying
往往就是最难被预言的事情
is one of life's less prophet-able occupations.
为什么有的黑奴比其他的贵
Why do some slaves cost more than others?
那些还年轻健康的
Ah, if they're still young and healthy,
或者能怀孕的女人  就贵一些
if the women can still conceive, they'll pay more.
把它放回盒子里去  小坏蛋
Put 'em back in the box, you scoundrel.
我们后天要还到
We'll return them to
加德纳先生的工作室去
Mr. Gardner's studio day after next.
小心一点
Be careful with 'em, now.
这手套就不该造出来
These things should've stayed on the calf.
斯莱德先生  您还是奴隶时
When you were a slave, Mr. Slade,
有人打你吗
did they beat you?
我生下来就是自由人
I was born a free man.
有人打我我会立刻还手的
Nobody beat me except I beat them right back.
林肯先生  你能跟我来吗
Mr. Lincoln, could you come with me
凯克莉女士曾是奴隶
Mrs. Keckley was a slave.
问问她被打过吗
Ask her if she was beaten.
你被打过吗  泰德
- Were you? - Tad!
我比你还小时被火铲打过
I was beaten with a fire shovel when I was younger than you.
您该去找林肯太太
You should go to Mrs. Lincoln.
她在威利的房间
She's in Willie's room.
她从不去那里
She never goes in there.
迎接队列已经在门口站好了
The reception line is already stretching out the door.
这地方15岁以上65岁以下
See, I'll be the only man over fifteen and under sixty-five
没穿军装的就只有我了
in this whole place not in uniform.
我不到15岁
I'm under fifteen.
我头很疼
My head hurts so.
威利死的那晚  我祈求一同死去
I prayed for death the night Willie died.
头痛让我知道我没能如愿
The headaches are how I know I didn't get my wish.
如何才能从白天熬到黑夜
How to endure the long afternoon that go deep into the night.
我知道
I know.
如何才能不去想他  我怎么做得到
Trying not to think about him. How will I manage?
总能做到的  能做到
- Somehow you will. -Somehow.
总能做到的  能做到的
Somehow. Somehow. Somehow
每次派对  每次
Every party, every
在这房子的四年里时刻在谴责我们
Four years more in this terrible house reproaching us.
他病得很厉害
He was a very sick little boy.
我们应该取消那个招待会  不是吗
We should've cancelled that reception, shouldn't we?
我们不知道他病得多重  我知道
- We didn't know how sick he was. - I knew, I knew
那晚我亲眼看到他奄奄一息
I saw that night he was dying.
三年前  战事正不断升级
Three years ago, the war was going so badly,
我们必须抛开情感强行振作
and we had to put on a face.
我看着威利死去  玛丽
- But I saw Willie was dying. - Mary.
我就这么眼睁睁看着  听我说
- I saw him. - Listen.
这对你来说很难
It's too hard.
太难了
Too hard.
招待会  1月15日
她只有10尺远
She's just ten feet yonder.
我可不想丢了饭碗
I'd like to keep my job.
萨姆纳议员  好久不见
Senator Sumner, it has been much too long.
您真是美艳动人
Oh, who can look on that celestial face and
这位是詹姆斯・阿什利  女士
- And - James Ashley, ma'am,
感谢上苍  感谢上苍 我们见过几次
We've met several times. Praise Heavens, praise Heavens,
我还以为今晚会十分无趣呢
just when I had abandoned hope of amusement,
这不是众议院筹款委员会主席吗
It's the Chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee!
林肯太太
Mrs. Lincoln.
请称呼我第一夫人
Madame President if you please.
千万别派下属委员会来调查我
Oh, don't convene another subcommittee to investigate me, sir!
我开玩笑呢
I'm teasing!
笑一个  韦德议员
Smile, Senator Wade.
我这就是在笑呢  林肯太太
I believe I am smiling, Mrs. Lincoln.
只要您家的财务没什么问题  夫人
As long as your household accounts are in order, Madame,
我们就不需要调查它们
we'll have no need to investigate them.
你一直都对我家的账本
You have always taken such a lively,
有着强烈的检察兴趣
even prosecutorial interest in my household accounts.
那是因为您家的账务让人感兴趣
Your household accounts have always been so interesting.
谢谢  这倒是真的
Yes, thank you, it's true,
摆平农务和伙食的账务可真是奇迹
the miracles I have wrought out of fertilizer bills and cutlery invoices,
不过我必须做到
but I had to!
四年前  当我和总统到这里时
Four years ago, when the president and I arrived,
这里跟猪窝一样
this was pure pigsty.
土耳其地毯上尽是烟草污渍
Tobacco stains in the turkey carpets.
天花板上长着月光般泛绿的蘑菇
Mushrooms, green as the moon, sprouting from the ceilings!
还有少得可怜的维护预算
And a pauper's pittance allotted for improvements.
似乎你们委员会同全华盛顿一起
As if your committee joined with all of Washington awaiting,
在这个你们期待成为我们舒适归宿的肮脏小窝里
in what you anticipated would be our comfort in squalor,
等着证明我们是来自草原的原始人
further proove that my husband and I were prairie primitives,
因人民选择的错误和民主制度的瑕疵
unsuited to the position to which an error of the people,
被推举到一个我们配不上的高位
a flaw in the democratic process, had elevated us.
过去就让它过去吧  新的一年到了
The past is the past, it's a new year now,
听说我们相处得还不错
and we are all getting along, or so they tell me.
我们要同心协力
I gather we are working together!
白宫和其他机构
The White House and the other House,
共同出谋划策
hatching little plans together.
母亲  怎么了
- Mother? - What?
人都堵在这了
You're creating a bottleneck.
我耽搁您太久了
Oh, I'm detaining you.
或者说  我耽搁您身后的人们太久了
And more importantly, the people behind you.
人民爱戴我的丈夫
How the people love my husband,
他们成群结队在公众日来看他
they flock to see him by their thousands on public days!
他们永远不会像爱他一样爱您
They will never love you the way they love him.
知道这些您一定很难受
How difficult it must be for you to know that.
但是记住这些也很重要
And yet how important to remember it.
明天的辩论中轮到我们发言
Since we have the floor next in the debate,
我建议你或许
I thought I'd suggest you might
缓和一下你的脾气
temper your contributions
免得吓到了保守派的朋友们
so as not to frighten our conservative friends?
阿什利说你在收买边缘的民主党人
Ashley insists you're ensuring approval by dispensing patronage
来保证修正案通过
to otherwise undeserving Democrats.
如果你要用土地挪用
I can't ensure a single damn thing
革命审判和惩罚
if you scare the whole House
吓唬整个议会的话
with talk of land appropriations,
我就什么都保证不了了
revolutionary tribunals, punitive
等战争结束  我想争取完全的平等
When the war ends, I intend to push for full equality,
赋予黑人选举权  当然远不只如此
the Negro vote, and much more.
国会将收复每一寸叛军土地
Congress shall mandate the seizure of every foot of rebel land
和他们的所有财产
and every dollar of their property.
我们要用充公的财富
We'll use their confiscated wealth
去建立成千上万黑人农民阶级
to establish hundreds of thousands of free Negro farmers,
和武装力量去占领和转换叛徒的遗产
and at their side soldiers armed to occupy and transform the heritage of traitors.
我们要建立一片
We'll build up a land down there
属于自由的男女老少的自由之地
of free men and free women and free children and freedom.
国家要知道我们的计划
The nation needs to know that we have such plans.
这是未加修饰的战后重建计划
That's the untempered version of reconstruction.
跟我想的不太一样
It's not quite exactly what I intend,
我们早晚会反对彼此的政见
but we shall oppose one another in the course of time.
但现在我们在同一条战线  所以我请求你
Now we're working together, and I'm asking you
耐心点  对吧
for patience, I expect.
当人民意见不一致
When the people disagree,
就需要慢慢让他们
bringing them together requires going slow
能够达成一致
till they're ready to make up.
去他的人民
Ah, shit on the people,
他们要什么  他们准备怎么样
and what they want, and what they're ready for,
我才不管他们要什么
I don't give a goddamn about the people and what they want!
这是一个长期为了人民的利益奋斗
This is the face of someone who has fought long and hard for the good of the people
却从不关心人民的人的面庞
without caring much for any of 'em.
我不带假发看起来更糟糕
And I look a lot worse without my wig.
人民选举了我  去代表他们
The people elected me! To represent them!
去领导他们  我成功领了他们  你应该试试
To lead them! And I lead! You ought to try it!
我欣赏你的热情  史蒂文斯先生
I admire your zeal, Mr. Stevens,
我也试过从中牟利
and I have tried to profit from the example of it.
如果听了你的  在萨穆特要塞战役
If I've listened to you,  I've declared every slave free
打响时就宣布奴隶解放
the minute the first shell struck Fort Sumter.
那么边境州将投向叛军
Then the border states would've gone over to the confederacy,
我们将输掉战争  失去联盟
the war would've been lost and the Union along with it,
不仅不能像我们预期那样
and instead of abolishing slavery,
在两周内废除奴隶制
as we hope to do in two weeks,
我们将无助地看着
we'll be watching helpless as infants as it spread
美国南部分裂出去
from the American South into South America.
你很渴望对我说这些吧
Oh God, how you have longed to say that to me.
你说你信任他们
You claim you trust them.
可你知道人民是什么样子
But you know what the people are.
在白人的心里本该引导他们的灵魂
You know that the inner compass
通往正义的罗盘
that should direct the soul toward justice
已经被邪恶的奴隶制
has ossified in white men and women, north and south, unto utter uselessness
僵化得毫无用处了
through tolerating the evil of slavery.
白人不能容忍
White people cannot bear the thought of sharing
与黑人共享这个国家无尽财富的想法
this country's infinite abundance with Negroes.
我在外勘测时发现关于罗盘
A compass, I learnt when I was surveying,
它会为你指出正北的方向
It'll point you True North from where you're standing,
却不会指出沿途会遇到的
but it'll got no advice about the swamps
沼泽  沙漠和深坑
and deserts and chasms that you'll encounter along the way.
如果在追寻目标的途中
If in pursuit of your destination,
你一往无前  不留心障碍困难
you plunge ahead, heedless of obstacles,
除了陷入沼泽哪里也到不了
and achieve nothing more than to sink in a swamp.
那么知道正北又有什么用
What's the use of knowing True North?
罗伯特会恳求我们让他入伍
Robert's gonna plead with us to let him enlist.
抽空跟罗比谈谈
Make time to talk to Robbie.
你总是陪着泰德  可是泰德还小
- You only have time for Tad. - But Tad's young.
罗伯特也很年轻
So is Robert.
去从军还太年轻了
Too young for the army.
很多比罗伯特更小的孩子都入伍了
Plenty of boys younger than Robert signing up.
不准让罗比去
Don't take Robbie.
别让我失去我的儿子
Don't let me lose my son.
走开  我们没空
Go away! We're occupied!
斯坦顿部长刚发来消息(埃德温・斯坦顿  美国战争部长)
Secretary Stanton has sent over to tell you
半个小时前
that as of half an hour ago,
对威尔明顿港的进攻开始了
the shelling of Wilmington harbor has commenced.
在这种攻击下他们坚持不了多久
They cannot possibly maintain under this kind of an assault.
特里有一万士兵围攻那个要塞
Terry's got ten thousand men surrounding the Goddamned fort,
他怎么还没回话
Why doesn't he answer my cables?
非瑟堡可大得很  埃德温
Fort Fisher is a mountain of a building, Edwin.
是他们最大的要塞了
It's the largest fort they have, sir.
每个壁垒都有22挺沿岸机枪
Twenty-two big seacoast guns on each rampart.
过去两年他们一直在加强防御
They've been reinforcing it for the last two years.
昨天开始他们一共挨了1万7千枚子弹
They've taken 17,000 shells since yesterday!
我要听到这要塞
I want to hear that Fort fisher is ours
和威尔明顿被攻陷的消息
and Wilmington has fallen!
再发一份电报
Send another damn cable!
问题就在他们的司令  怀丁
The problem's their commander. Whiting!
他亲自指挥修建了堡垒  那玩意是他的亲儿子
He engineered the fortress himself. The damned thing's his child.
他会拼到最后一兵一卒  不会
He'll defend it till his every last man is gone. He is not thinking
滚出来  你这臭老鼠
Come on out, you old rat!
那就是
That's what
1776年伊森・艾伦对
That' what Ethan Allen called
蒂康德罗格要塞的指挥官说的话
to the commander of Fort Ticonderogain in 1776.
滚出来  你这臭老鼠
Come on out, you old rat!
因为蒂康德罗格里
Aah, 'course there were only
只有40多个英国兵了
forty odd redcoats at Ticonderoga.
有一个关于伊森・艾伦的故事
But there is one Ethan Allen story that
不  我很喜欢
- No! - I'm very partial to.
你又要讲故事了
No, you're going to tell a story!
真不敢相信
I don't believe that I can bear
在这种时候我还要忍受你的另一个故事
to listen to another one of your stories right now!
我要看侧线攻击亚历山大市的计划
I need the B&O sideyard schedules for Alexandria!
我今天早上就说过了
I asked for them this morning!
在独立战争偃旗息鼓时
It was right after the Revolution,
在和平女神降临美利坚大地后
right after peace had been concluded,
伊森・艾伦去了伦敦和国王处理
Ethan Allen went to London to help
我们新生国家的相关事宜
our new country conduct its business with the king.
不管到哪里英国人总嘲笑我们粗野
The English sneered at how rough we are,
鲁莽和愚笨之类的
and rude and simple-minded and on like that,
有一天他被邀请
everywhere he went, till one day he was
去一个英国贵族的别墅
invited to the townhouse of a great English lord.
吃过晚餐  喝过饮料
Dinner was served, beverages imbibed,
时间慢慢过去
time passed, as happens, and
艾伦先生想上厕所
Mr. Allen found he needed the privy.
于是有人带他去洗手间  他十分感激
He was grateful to be directed thence.
或者说是十分爽
Relieved, you might say.
可艾伦先生发现厕所门口
Now, Mr. Allen discovered on entering the water closet
唯一的装饰品居然是
that the only decoration therein was a
乔治・华盛顿的雕像
a portrait of George Washington.
伊森・艾伦方便完之后
Ethan Allen done what he came to do,
回到了会客厅
and returned to the drawing room.
主人和其他客人都很失望
His host and the others were disappointed
因为他没有提到华盛顿的雕像
when he didn't mention Washington's portrait.
终于主人忍不住了
And finally His Lordship couldn't resist,
他问艾伦先生有没有注意到
and asked Mr. Allen had he noticed it,
华盛顿的头像
the picture of Washington.
他看到了
He had.
那么他觉得那位置怎么样
What did he think of its placement,
放在那里对艾伦先生来说是否合适
did it seem appropriately located to Mr. Allen?
艾伦先生说很合适
Mr. Allen said it did.
主人很吃惊  很合适吗
His host was astounded! Appropriate?
乔治・华盛顿的肖像放在厕所里
George Washington's likeness in a water closet?
是的  艾伦说道
Yes, said Mr. Allen,
它在那里很起作用
where it'll do good service.
没有什么比华盛顿的目光更能
The whole world knows nothing'll make an Englishman shit
让英国人尿裤子了
quicker than the sight of George Washington.
我喜欢这个故事
I love that story.
非瑟堡是我们的了
Fort Fisher is ours.
我们攻下来了
We're taken the port.
那威尔明顿呢
And Wilmington?
要塞攻下来了
We're taken the fort,
威尔明顿市还没有投降
but the city of Wilmington has not surrendered.
伤亡多少
How many casualties?
(纽约先驱论坛报
威尔明顿的沦陷)
损失很严重
Heavy losses.
还在不断增多
And more to come.
举国悲痛
Sours the national mood.
这或许足够让他气馁
That might suffice to discourage him.
放弃这个吗
To bring this down?
不太可能  这是生死厮杀
Not in a fight like this. This is to the death.
真可怕
It's gruesome!
你在绝望还是想偷懒
Are you despairing, or merely lazy?
这场战争是为美利坚合众国而打响
This fight is for The united States of America.
没什么足够
Nothing suffices
一个谣言  不可能
A rumor? Nothing!
他们可没偷懒  他们在收买投票
They're not lazy. They're busily buying votes!
而我们还想着靠举国悲痛来赢吗
While we hope to be saved by the national mood?!
趁着还有救  等史蒂文斯下次发言
Before this blood is dry, when Stevens next takes the floor,
嘲讽他  你很擅长这个
taunt him. You excel at that.
让他说出他内心深处的话
Get him to proclaim what we all know he believes in his coal-colored heart:
这场投票是为了抬高黑人
that this vote is meant to set the black race on high,
是为了黑化美国
to niggerate America.
乔治  不要气馁
George, please. Stay on course.
想办法激怒史蒂文斯
Bring Stevens to full froth.
我能确保
I can ensure that every
从路易斯维尔到旧金山的记者
newspaperman from Louisville to San Francisco
都会来见证和报道的
will be here to witness it and print it.
下面有请优雅的绅士
The floor belongs to the mellifluent gentleman
来自肯塔基的乔治・伊曼
from Kentucky, Mr. George Yeaman.
谢谢  科尔法议长
I thank you, Speaker Colfax.
尽管  我对奴隶制深恶痛绝
Although I'm disgusted by slavery
站在沉痛悲哀的今天
I rise on this sad and solemn day.
我要说我反对这项修正案
to announce that I'm opposed to the amendment.
我们要考虑如果40万有色人种
We must consider what will become of colored folk
一瞬间全部获得自由会怎么样
if four million are in one instant set free.
他们就自由了  乔治
They'll be free, George.
就是这样
That's what'll become of them!
想想如果伊曼先生倒戈了该多妙
Think how splendid if Mr. Yeaman switched.
公开反对我们  他不会倒戈了
Too publicly against us. He can't change course now.
不用点特殊办法是不行
Not for some miserable little job anyways.
我们将被迫解放赋予色人种政治权利
We will be forced to enfranchise the men of the colored race.
因为不这样做是没有人性的
It would be inhuman not to!
可是我们有谁想给黑鬼选举权
Who among us is prepared to give Negroes the vote?
那接下来又是什么
What shall follow upon that?
全社会共享政治权利吗
Universal enfranchisement?
女性也获得投票权吗
Votes for women?
这不是俄亥俄  米勒斯堡的
Bless my eyes, if it isn't the Post Master
邮政局长吗
of Millersburg Ohio!
莱克勒克先生认为在道义上
Mr. LeClerk felt honor-bound to
有责任告诉我们你的无耻背叛
inform us of your disgusting betrayal.
你出卖了灵魂
Your prostitution.
是吗  霍金斯局长
Is that true, Postmaster Hawkins?
你的贞操一文不值吗
Is your maidenly virtue for sale?
如果我的邻居知道我投票支持黑奴自由
If my neighbors hear that I voted yes for nigger freedom
而不是和平  他们会杀了我的
and no to peace, they will kill me.
在商言商  你的人不会只因有谈和的传言
A deal is a deal and you men know better than to piss your pants
就要取你的项上人头的
just because there's talk about peace talks.
我会找到新工作的
Look, I'll find another job.
我的邻居在纳什维尔
My neighbors in Nashville,
他们知道我效忠联邦
they found out I was loyal to the Union,
还拿刀子想阉我
they came after me with gelding knives!
什么工作都行  别走错路了  克莱・霍金斯
- Any other job! - You do right, Clay Hawkins
我也不想走错  还能大赚一笔
- I want to do right! - and make yourself some money in the bargain
可我没有勇气
But I got no courage!
等等  你是想当西部保留地的税务官
Wait!! You wanted, what was it, tax man for the Western Reserve,
还是想拥有整个俄亥俄都行  只要
hell you can have the whole state of Ohio if you
该死
Aw, crap.
11票
Eleven votes?!
两天前还有12票  怎么回事
Two days ago we had twelve! What happened?
里士满变节了
There are defections in the Richmond
是那个流言吗
It's the goddamned rumors regarding
是的  和谈的传言  无稽之谈
- Yes! The peace offer! - Groundless.
我早说过了  但是谣言还是不断
- I told you that. - And yet the rumors persist.
这会毁了我们
They are ruining us.
在剩下的这些不怎么可靠的代表中
Among the few remaining representatives who seem remotely plausible
有些人开始表现出立场摇摆
there is a perceptible increase in resistance.
该死
Resistance, hell!
辛纳曼鲍勃・霍利斯特
Thingamabob Hollister,
来自印第安纳的民主党人
Dem from Indiana?
我接近他的时候  那婊子差点杀了我
I approached him, the sumbitch near to murdered me!
你可能太过强硬
Perhaps you push too hard.
我一点也没有
I push nobody.
也许我们需要后援
Perhaps we need reinforcements.
如果杰夫・戴维斯要来和谈
If Jeff Davis wants to cease hostilities,
还有谁真的关心解放黑奴
who do you think'll give a genuine solid shit to free slaves?
回去工作吧
Get back to it.
先生们  再会
And gentlemen, good day.
我们死路一条了
We are at an impasse.
让林肯去公开地否认谣言
Tell Lincoln to deny the rumors. Publicly.
你指望我们干什么
Tell us what you expect of us.
我指望你们去工作
I expect you to do your work.
要有健全的感觉和品味
And to have sufficient sense and taste
不要试图对总统指手画脚
not to presume to instruct the President.
或是对我
Or me.
到底有没有和谈
Is there a Confederate offer or not?
尤里西斯・格兰特(美军总指挥官)
先生们
Gentlemen
我建议你们在把提议交给总统前
I suggest you work some changes to your proposal
能够做一些修改
before you give it to the President.
我们急着返回华盛顿
We're eager to be on our way to Washington.
林肯先生派你来就是告诉我们这些的吗
Did Mr. Lincoln tell you to tell us this?
上面说  为两国谋求和平
It says securing peace for our two countries.
后文也是这样
And it goes on like that.
不知道你是说
I don't know what you
只有一个国家
There's just one country.
而你和我  我们都是这个国家的公民
And you and I, we're citizens of that country.
我为了从武装叛军手中保卫她而战
I'm fighting to protect it from armed rebels.
也就是你们
From you.
布莱尔先生告诉我们
Mr. Blair, he told us,
他跟戴维斯总统说我们
he told President Davis we were
公民普雷斯顿・布莱尔可以随意信口开河
A private citizen like Preston Blair can say what he pleases
因为他没有任何权利
since he has no authority over anything.
如果想要和林肯总统和谈
If you want to discuss peace with President Lincoln,
就得修改它
consider revisions.
如果我们不以交战两国的名义谈论停战
If we're not to discuss a truce between warring nations,
那么我们到底在讨论什么
what in heaven's name can we discuss?
投降的条件
Terms of surrender.
美国军事办公室电报处
Office United States Military Telegraph War Dept.
致亚伯拉罕・林肯
For Abraham Lincoln,
美国总统  1865年1月20日
President of the United States, January 20, 1865.
我将此消息秘密送出
I will state confidentially that I am convinced,
在和对方代表谈判后
upon conversation with these Commissioners,
我认为他们的目的友好  意图诚挚
that their intentions are good and their desire sincere
旨在恢复和平与联合
to restore peace and union.
我恐怕他们现在
I fear now their going back,
若不带回我方高层
without any expression of interest
意图再次和谈的兴趣
from anyone in authority,
会对林肯先生影响很不好
Mr. Lincoln will have a bad influence.
很抱歉我没能为您
I will be sorry should it prove impossible for you
安排与他们会面
to have an interview with them.
等待您的指示
I am awaiting your instructions.
尤利西斯・格兰特  美军中将
U.S. Grant, Lieutenant General Commanding Armies United States.
四年的战争  近60万人丧生
After four years of war and near 600,000 lives lost,
他相信我们现在就能停战
he believes we can end this war now.
我对他信任有加
My trust in him is marrow deep.
你能让代表来华盛顿
You could bring the delegates to Washington.
作为交换让南方立刻投降
In exchange for the South's immediate surrender,
我们向他们保证修正案不会通过
we could promise them the amendment's defeat.
他们会同意  你觉得呢
They'd agree, don't you think?
那么我们在这周就能停止战争
We'd end the war. This week.
如果你不想这样  除非你能
Or if you could manage, without seeming to do it, to.
和谈代表团可能会
The peace delegation might encounter delays
在詹姆斯河附近耽搁一阵子
as they travel up the James River.
尤其是威尔明顿还在交战
Particularly with the fighting around Wilmington.
10天时间之内
Within ten days time,
我们或许可以让第13修正案通过
we might pass the Thirteenth Amendment.
一名16岁的男孩
Here's a sixteen year old boy.
他将要被吊死
They're gonna hang him.
他和第15  印第安纳骑兵队一起
He was with the 15th Indiana Calvary
在伯弗附近
near Beaufort,
他似乎打断了马腿想当逃兵
seems he lamed his horse to avoid battle.
如果我赦免他
I don't think even Stanton would complain
我想连斯坦顿都不会抱怨的
if I pardoned him,
你觉得斯坦顿会说什么吗
You think Stanton would complain?
我不知道  先生  我不知道您是谁
I don't know, sir, I don't know who you're, uh
现在几点了
What time is it?
早上3点40分
It's three forty in the morning.
别让他再赦免逃兵了
Don't let him pardon any more deserters
斯坦顿先生认为您赦免了太多了
Aah, Mr. Stanton thinks you pardon too many.
他对这一点很恼火
He's generally apoplectic on the subject.
他不应该那样做
He oughtn't to have done that,
把马弄残废  太残忍了
crippled his horse, that was cruel,
但也不能就这么吊死一个16岁的男孩吧
but you don't just hang a sixteen year old boy for that.
问问那匹马怎么想
Ask the horse what he thinks.
没有几个16岁的男孩能活下来 因为残忍
For cruelty. There'd be no sixteen year old boys left.
格兰特想要我
Grant wants me to
让南方叛党的代表团来华盛顿
bring the secesh delegates to Washington.
真有南方人的代表吗
So there are secesh delegates?
他只是害怕了而已
He was afraid, that's all it was.
我也不在乎绞死一个怯战的男孩
I don't care to hang a boy for being frightened, either.
但这么做有什么好处呢
What good would it do him?
战争就要结束了  不是吗
War's nearly done, ain't that so?
多一具尸体有什么意义呢
What use one more corpse?
多几具尸体又有什么意义呢
Any more corpses?
要我陪您吗
Do you need company?
这种时候  我一个人就行
In times like this, I'm best alone.
致陆军总司令尤利西斯・格兰特  锡蒂波因特
Lieutenant General Ulysses S. Grant, City Point.
我极有诚意的读完您的电报
I have read your words with interest.
不论我如何应对里士满官员来访一事
I ask that, regardless of any action I take
我要求您
in the matter of the visit of the Richmond commissioners,
请您务必让军队
you maintain among your troops military preparedness for battle,
一如既往地时刻保持备战状态
as you have done until now.
请桑德斯上尉带该特使团前来华盛顿与我商谈
Have Captain Saunders convey the commissioners to me here in Washington.
亚伯拉罕・林肯再加上日期  好的  先生
- A. Lincoln and the date. - Yes sir.
现在就发吗  先生
Shall I transmit, sir?
我们能决定自己的出生吗
You think we choose to be born?
我觉得不能
I don't suppose so.
我们是不是生逢其时
Are we fitted to the times we're born into?
我不知道自己是不是
Well, I don't know about myself.
但您也许是的  先生
You may be sir. Fitted.
你是怎么想的
What do you reckon?
我是名工程师
Well, I'm an engineer.
这个时代有机械  但是没有人天生就适合
I reckon there's machinery but No one's done the fitting.
你是名工程师
You're an engineer.
那一定知道欧几里得的定理和公理
You must know Euclid's axioms and common notions.
我在学校学过  但是
I must've in school, but
我受过的学校教育不多
I never had much of schooling,
但是在一本借到的旧书上
but I read Euclid,
读过欧几里得
in an old book I borrowed.
这里没有理解住多少  但是
Little enough ever found its way in here, but
一旦学会就永远都记得
once learnt it stayed learnt.
欧几里得的第一条公理就是
Euclid's first common notion is this:
等于同量的量彼此相等
Things which are equal to the same thing are equal to each other.
这是数理的规则
That's a rule of mathematical reasoning.
它是对的  因为适用
It's true because it works.
能而且永远适用
Has done and always will do.
在书里
In his book, hmm
欧几里得称此为自证
Euclid says this is self-evident.
看到吗  就算是两千年前的数理定律
D'you see, there it is, even in that two thousand year old book of mechanical law:
也认为  等于同量的量彼此相等这个道理
it is a self evident truth that things which are equal to the same thing
是不证自明的
are equal to each other.
我们生而平等
We begin with equality.
这才是世界的起源  不是吗
That's the origin, isn't it?
这种平等  我们称之为  公平
That balance, that's that's fairness.
称之为正义
That's justice.
请把最后一句念给我听
Just read me back the last sentence of that telegram, please.
请桑德斯上尉带该特使团前来华盛顿与我商谈
Have Captain Saunders convey the commissioners to me here in Washington.
做点小改动吧  山姆
A slight emendation if you would, Sam.
请桑德斯上尉带领该特使团
Have Captain Saunders convey the gentlemen
到达弗吉尼亚州的汉普顿港群
aboard the River Queen
登上河流女王号
as far as Hampton Roads, Virginia,
之后  原地等待
and there wait until
我的后续指令
further advice from me.
切勿前往华盛顿
Do not proceed to Washington.
环球报  先驱报
The World, the Herald
泰晤士报  纽约客  芝加哥报
and the Times, New York, Chicago,
商业日报  甚至你家乡的小报都来了
the Journal of Commerce, even your hometown paper's here.
万分恳请您
Say you believe
告诉他们你只认可不同种族的法律地位平等
only in legal equality for all races,
而不是种族平等
not racial quality. I beg you, sir.
要么听我劝告
Compromise.
要么以身犯险
Or you risk it all.
史蒂文斯先生  我有个问题要问您
I've asked you a question, Mr. Stevens,
也请您回答我
and you must answer me.
您是否认为要按字面的意思
Do you or do you not hold that the precept that
去理解人人生而平等
all men are created equal is meant literally?
这难道不是修正案的真实目的吗
Is that not the true purpose of the amendment?
用以实现您的终极野心  来提升
To promote your ultimate and ardent dream to elevate
修正案的真正目的  伍德先生
The true purpose of the amendment, Mr. Wood,
难道是您说的那些虚有其表
you perfectly-named,
肤浅至极  繁琐不堪的东西吗
brainless, obstructive object?
史蒂文斯先生  您一直坚持认为
Now you have always insisted, Mr. Stevens,
黑人和我们白人是一样的
that Negroes are the same as white men are.
修正案的真正目的
The true purpose of the amendment
我并非肯定一切平等
I don't hold with equality in all things,
而只是承认他们的法律地位平等
only with equality before the law and nothing more.
不是这样  你
That's not so! You
你是认为黑人和白人完全一样
You believe that Negroes are entirely equal to white men.
你之前无数次这样表态
You've said it a thousand times
不知羞  不知羞
For shame! For shame!
不要再闪烁其词了  伍德议员
Stop prevaricating and answer, Representative Wood!
我不认为人人生来一切平等
I don't hold with equality in all things,
而只是承认法律面前人人平等
only with equality before the law
这么多年了仅此而已
- After the decades- And nothing more!
他在回答你的问题
He's answered your questions!
这个修正案和种族平等没有关系
This amendment has naught to do with race equality!
我不认为人人生来一切平等  你一直以来都坚持的观点呢
- I don't hold with equality in all things - You have long insisted, have you not
只是法律面前人人平等  难道认为有色人种
- only with equality before the law - that the dusk colored race
仅此而已  和白色人种不一样
- and nothing more. - is no different from the white one.
想不到这老头子竟然能装到现在
Who'd ever've guessed that old nightmare capable of such control?
说不定哪一天他就能成为一名政治家
He might make a politician someday
我要出去会  肯克莱太太
- I need to go. - Mrs. Keykley!
你这种含糊其辞的做法
Your frantic attempt to delude us now
真是不配做一个议员
is unworthy of a representative.
事实上  甚至不配做一个白人公民
It is in fact, unworthy of a white man!
当我面前站着一个来自俄亥俄州
How can I hold that all men are created equal,
臭气熏天  道德沦丧的男人
when here before me stands, stinking,
你让我怎么相信人类的一切均为平等
the moral carcass of the gentleman from Ohio,
这不就是劣等人存在的证明吗
proof that some men are inferior,
造物主只给予了他们最低等的智慧
endowed by their Maker with dim wits,
血管里流淌的不是鲜红炽热的鲜血
impermeable to reason with cold pallid slime
而是冰冷呆滞的泥浆
in their veins instead of hot red blood!
比起人类  你更像爬行动物  乔治
You are more reptile than man, George,
如此的低下渺小
so low and flat
以至于人类无法用脚把你踩死
that the foot of man is incapable of crushing you!
胆大包天
How dare you!
即使是你  彭德尔顿
Yet even you, Pendleton,
早就该因叛国罪被送上绞刑架的你
who should have been gibbetted for treason long before today,
即使一文不值  也该被法律平等对待
even worthless unworthy you ought to be treated equally before the law!
因此  先生  我再一再二再三强调
And so again, sir, and again and again and again I say:
我不认为人人生来一切平等
I DO NOT HOLD WITH EQUALITY IN ALL THINGS.
我认同的是法律面前人人平等
ONLY WITH EQUALITY BEFORE THE LAW.
议长先生  您竟然容许这种无耻粗俗的人
Mr. Speaker, will you permit this vile boorish man
诽谤我  威胁我
to slander ant to threaten me and
您问过我  我什么时候惊讶过
You asked if ever I was surprised.
就在今天  史蒂文斯先生
Today Mr. Stevens,
我十分震惊
I was surprised.
您为了种族平等斗争30年
You've led the battle for race equality for thirty years!
这是国家未来的基石
The basis of of every hope for this country's future life,
现在您却否认黑人的权利  真令人作呕
you denied Negro equality! I'm nauseated.
您否认人人都有生而为人的权利
You refused to say that all humans are, well human!
您出卖了自己的灵魂吗  史蒂文斯先生
Have you lost your very soul, Mr. Stevens
您不是什么都敢说吗
Is there nothing you won't say?
真抱歉让你恶心阿萨  这肯定让人不适
I'm sorry you're nauseous, Asa, that must be unpleasant.
我希望修正案能通过
I want the amendment to pass.
这样宪法中唯一关于奴隶制的表述便是
So that the Constitution's first and only mention of slavery
它毫无疑问应该被废除
is its absolute prohibition.
为了修正案  为了我终生的事业
For this amendment, for which I have worked all of my life
为了无数为争取权利而牺牲的黑人
and for which countless colored men and women have fought and died
现在  也为了那些护国安邦的将士
and now hundreds of thousands of soldiers.
我没有出卖灵魂  先生  没有
No, sir, no.
也没有什么事不敢说的
It seems there is very nearly nothing I won't say.
我不进去了
I'm not going in.
你说过想帮我
You said you wanted to help me.
这  这只不过是你想让我丧失斗志的把戏
This is This is just a clumsy attempt at discouragement.
我去过战地医院  见过那些外科手术
I've been to army hospitals, I've seen surgeries,
我还和妈妈一起去过疟疾横行的驳船
I went and visited the malaria barges with mama.
她说她没带你进去
She told me she didn't take you inside.
我之后偷偷溜进去了
I snuck in afterwards.
我知道那是什么样子  你吓不到我
I've seen what it's like, this changes nothing.
不管怎么说  很高兴你能陪我来
At all rates, I'm happy to have your company.
早上好  吉姆
Morning, Jim.
早上好  总统先生
Hello, Mr. President.
很高兴又见到你
Good to see you again.
小伙子们  第一个问题  吃得好吗
Well boys, first question: You getting enough to eat?
你好  先生
Hello, sir.
你叫什名字  战士  罗伯特
- What's your name, soldier? - Robert.
罗伯特  很高兴见到你  罗伯特
Robert. Good to meet you, Robert.
很高兴见到您
Nice to meet you.
你叫什名字  凯文
- What's your name? - Kevin.
我经过时告诉我你们的名字
Tell me your names as I go past.
我希望知道你们的名字  凯文是吗
I like to know who I'm talkin' to. Kevin.
总统先生  约翰  约翰
- Mr. President, John. - John.
我见过你  总统先生
- I've seen you before. - Mr. President
一定要吃些肉  我不会介意
Make sure you get some steak, I wouldn't mind
怎么了  鲍勃
What's the matter, Bob?
我要参军
I have to do this!
我要参军  我入伍不需要经过你的同意
And I will do it and I don't need your permission to enlist.
从战争开始  有多少儿子
That same speech has been made by how many sons,
对他们的父亲说过一样的话
to how many fathers since the war began?
我才不需要你该死的许可  老家伙
I don't need your damn permission, you miserable old goat,
无论如何我都会参军
I'm gonna enlist anyhow!
又有多少父亲对他们儿子
And what wouldn't those numberless fathers have given
说出我要对你说出的这番话
to be able to say to their sons as I now say to mine,
我才是总司令
I'm commander-in-chief,
没有我的允许
so in point of fact, without my permission,
你不能参军  年轻人
you ain't enlisting in nothing, nowhere, young man.
你只是怕妈妈  根本不是担心我的死活
It's mama you're scared of, not me getting killed.
我必须参军  我一定会的
I have to do this! And I will!
不然余生我都会以此为耻
Or I will feel ashamed of myself for the rest of my life.
能不能上战场根本无所谓
Whether or not you fought is what's gonna matter.
这不仅仅是为了别人  也是为了我自己
And not just to other people, but to myself.
我成不了您  爸爸  我办不到
I won't be you, pa. I can't do that.
但是我不想碌碌无为
But I don't want to be nothing.
他会没事的  玛丽
He'll be fine, Mary.
锡蒂波因特离前线有一段距离
City Point's away back from the front lines, from the fighting,
他会被安排去做格兰特将军传信的副官
he'll be an adjutant running messages for General Grant.
战争会要了我们儿子的命
The war will take our son!
那些狙击手  弹片  伤寒
A sniper, or a shrapnel shell, or typhus!
像威利一样
Same as took Willie,
每天都有成百上千的孩子在那死去
it takes hundreds of boys a day!
他只会成为无谓的牺牲品
He'll die uselessly,
到时候你让我怎么原谅你
and how will I ever forgive you?
大多数人  都最喜欢长子长女  但是你
Most men, their firstborn is their favorite, but you,
你却一直责怪罗伯特的出生
you've always blamed Robert for being born,
说那让你为婚姻所困  让你陷入不幸
for trapping you in a marriage that's only ever given you grief
让你后悔  不是这样
- and caused you regret. - That's simply not true.
如果冷泉港那样的屠杀再发生(1864年5月冷泉港战役  北军伤亡5万多人  南军只损失约2万人)
And if the slaughter of Cold Harbor is on your hands same as Grant,
我们只能祈求上帝相助
God help us!
我们要为你犯下的那些数不清的屠杀付出代价
We'll pay for the oceans of spilled blood you've sanctioned,
我们的儿子会用他的鲜血
the uncountable corpses we'll be made to pay
为那些堆积如山的尸骨做陪葬
with our son's dear blood.
就这次  就这次  林肯夫人
Just, just this once, Mrs. Lincoln,
我求你用解放人类而不是自私的观点来看问题
I demand of you to try and take the liberal and not the selfish point of view.
如果我们继续扼杀他的发自内心的抱负
Robert will never forgive himself. You imagine he'll forgive us
罗伯特将永远无法原谅自己  你还能奢望他原谅我们吗
if we continue to stifle his very natural ambition?!
如果我不同意呢
And if I refuse to take the highroad,
如果我无法再背负更多痛苦了呢
if I won't take up the rough old cross,
你是不是又要威胁我  送我去疯人院
will you threaten me again with the madhouse,
就像我无法停止为威利的死终日哭泣时那样
as you did when I couldn't stop crying over Willie,
就像我让你看到什么是真的心碎的时候那样
when I showed you what heartbreak, real heartbreak looked like,
而你根本就没有勇气面对  没有勇气帮我
and you hadn't the courage to countenance it, to help me
没错  当你拒绝去安慰泰德的时候
That's right. When you refused so much as to comfort Tad
那孩子不仅仅身体不好  我当时在房间里陪着威利
- the child who was not only sick - I was in the room with Willie,
还极度悲伤  我那时正抱着他
- but beside himself with grief? - I was holding him
但你只想着你的悲伤  你的悲伤  他死在了我怀里
- Oh but your grief, your grief, your- in my arms as he died!
无穷无尽的悲伤  你怎么敢这样说我
- inexhaustible grief! - How dare you throw that at me?!
他的母亲居然不让他靠近自己  我不能让泰德进来
- And his mother won't let him near her, - I couldn't let Tad in!
因为她一天到晚都在不停尖叫  我不想让他
- 'cos she's screaming from morning to night, - I couldn't risk him
你在走廊上乱晃  看见我生气的样子
- pacing the corridors - seeing how angry I was!
对着影子家具和鬼魂大喊大叫
howling at shadows and furniture and ghosts!
我早就该你去疯人院
I ought to have done it,
为了泰德我早就该这么做
I ought have done for Tad's sake,
为了每一个人  我早就该送你去疯人院
for everybody's goddamned sake, I should have clapped you in the madhouse!
你送啊
Then do it!!
来啊  别只威胁我
Do it! Don't you threaten me,
你快来吧  把我锁起来
you do it this time, lock me away!
你一定会的  我发誓  如果罗伯特死了的话
You'll have to, I swear! If Robert is killed
我不能忍受你再为威利难过
I couldn't tolerate you grieving so for Willie
因为我也不会允许自己这么做
because I couldn't permit it in myself,
尽管我希望如此  玛丽
though I wanted to, Mary.
我想过陪他入土  守着他的灵柩
I wanted to crawl under the earth, into the vault with his coffin.
而且我现在依旧这样想
And I still do.
无时无刻不这么想
Everyday I do.
所以不要跟我讲悲伤
Don't speak to me about grief.
鲍勃  你还有我  都必须要做出自己的决定
I must make my decisions, Bob must make his, you yours.
必须承担我们要承担的  忍受我们要忍受的
And bear what we must, hold and carry what we must.
当我忍受这些时  你要允许我
What I carry within me, you must allow me to do it,
独自承受自己必须承受的  你也一样  玛丽
alone as I must. And you alone, Mary,
承受你自己的部分
you alone
这样可以减轻彼此的负担
may lighten this burden,
或者你可以选择  把一切推向崩溃
or render it intolerable. As you choose.
歌剧为浮士德
你以为我不知道你在做什么吗
You think I'm ignorant of what you're up to
你以为你打算不跟我商量这些事
because you haven't discussed this scheme
我就不知道了吗
with me as you ought to have done.
我什么时候那么好糊弄
When have I ever been so easily bamboozled?
当你坚持要让修正案通过
I believe you
要废除奴隶制的时候
when you insist that amending the constitution
我相信你
and abolishing slavery will end this war.
但是既然你把我们的儿子送上战场
And since you are sending my son into the war,
不让修正案通过  你就等着吃苦头吧
woe unto you if you fail to pass the amendment.
苏厄德不想最后弄得政以贿成
Seward doesn't want me leaving big muddy footprints all over town.
你比谁都清楚
No one has ever lived who knows better than you
官场上的那些权谋算计
the proper placement of footfalls on treacherous paths.
苏厄德不做  你就要去做
Seward can't do it. You must.
如果你不能拿到必要的选票
Because if you fail to acquire the necessary votes,
你就麻烦了  想想到时候你怎么向我交代
woe unto you, sir, you will answer to me.
我知道还有4天就要投票了
I know the vote is only four days away.
我知道您很担心
I know you're concerned.
谢谢您为这件事如此操劳
Thank you for your concern over this,
我想告诉您  修正案会通过的
and I want you to know, they'll approve it.
上帝会保佑的
God will see to it.
我可不羡慕上帝的工作
I don't envy him His task.
相对于去向众议员拉票
He may wish He'd chosen an instrument for His purpose
他可能会采取一种更加合适的方法来实现目的
more wieldy than the House of Representatives.
那么你会确保它通过的
Then you'll see to it.
你有没有担心过你们的未来
Are you afraid of what lies ahead for your people?
如果我们通过了
If we succeed?
白人不会希望我们呆在这
White people don't want us here.
很多人可能不会  您呢
- Many don't. - What about you?
我并不了解您  凯克莉夫人
I don't know you, Mrs. Keckley.
不了解你们的任何一员
Any of you.
我很熟悉你们  你们所有人
You're familiar to me, as all people are.
我眼中的你们
Unaccommodated, poor, bare,
居无定所  食不果腹  贫穷却又勤劳
forked creatures such as we all are.
但是你们有权利期待我所期待的一切
You have a right to expect what I expect,
我们也能理解彼此的期盼
and likely our expectations are not incomprehensible to each other.
我知道我能习惯你们
I assume I'll get used to you.
但是你们对于这个国家意味着什么
But what you are to the nation,
你们被解放后的未来  我并不知道会怎样
what'll become of you once slavery's day is done, I don't know.
我不知道我的同胞是怎么想的
What my people are to be, I can't say.
黑人们一直在为自由而战斗牺牲
Negroes have been fighting and dying for freedom
因为我们是第一批奴隶
since the first of us was a slave.
我从未听说有人过问自由会带来什么
I never heard any ask what freedom will bring.
因为首先要得到自由
Freedom's a first.
至于我
As for me
我的儿子身穿联军的蓝色制服
My son died, fighting for the Union
为联军战死沙场
wearing the Union blue.
为了自由而牺牲
For freedom he died.
我是他的母亲
I'm his mother.
这就是我对国家的意义  林肯先生
That's what I am to the nation, Mr. Lincoln.
仅此而已
What else must I be?
不要多久我就能凑手好牌
My whole hand's gonna be proud in about five seconds.
是吗  那我倒要看看  让你看看我的牌
- Oh, it is? What you got goin'? - Let's see how proud you gonna be.
干什么  走开
- Yeah? - Go away!
那个表链是金的吗  别盯着我的表带
- That watch fob, is that gold? - You keep your eyes off my fob!
先生们  对9
- Gentlemen - Nines paired!
有客人来了  去你的
- you have a visitor. - Oh my God damn!
好吧  这下完蛋了
Well, I'll be fucked.
我也是这么想的  您是
I wouldn't bet against it, Mr?
比尔博  比尔博先生
- W.N. Bilbo. - Yeah, Mr. Bilbo.
先生们  先生
- Gentlemen. - Sir
您怎么在这里  我无意冒犯
Why are you here? No offense, but Mr. Seward's
但苏厄德先生不允许我们提起您的名字
banished the very mention of your name,
他甚至不允许我们用5美元的钞票(林肯绿币  南北战争前  林肯为筹集战争资金而发行的一种债券)
he won't even let us use fifty-cent pieces
因为上面印有您的头像
'cause they got your face on 'em.
国务卿告诉我
The Secretary of State here tells me that, uh,
你们从民主党那里争取到11张选票  真不错
you got eleven Democrats in the bag, that's encouraging.
您不会为了11张选票而高兴的
Oh, you've got no cause to be encouraged,
先生
Sir. Uh
我们被解雇了吗
Are we being fired?
我们可都听到午夜的钟声了  夏禄先生(莎士比亚《亨利四世》)
We have heard the chimes of midnight, Master Shallow.
我来这是为了告诉你们  胜利的钟声就要敲响
I'm here to alert you boys that the great day of reckoning is nigh upon us.
我们还没有把民主党的票收入囊中呢
The Democrats we've yet to bag, sir.
利诱还远远不够
The patronage jobs simply won't bag 'em.
他们想要  更有说服力的东西  总统先生
They require more convincing, Mr. President.
帮我个忙  好吗
Do me a favor, will ya?
当然
Sure.
我今早看了下报纸
I snagged my eye in the paper this morning,
看到科廷州长计划公布
and Governor Curtin is set to declare a winner in the
在饱受争议的国会选举中的胜出者
disputed Congressional election for the
宾夕法尼亚16区的
Pennsylvania 16th District.
没错  很高兴有人能跟上我的思路
District. What a joy to be comprehended.
那位议员打算亲自去拜访科廷州长
Hop on a train to Philadell, call on the Governor
让莱瑟姆或者谢尔去一趟
Send Latham. Or Schell.
不  他能做好的  好好磨练一番总是能行的
No, he'll do fine, just polish yourself up first.
他可是州长钦定的
The incumbent is claiming he won it.
名字是  科夫罗斯
- Name of, uh - Coffroth.
没错  就是他  科夫罗斯
- That's him. - Coffroth.
他是个民主党  我知道
- He is a Democrat. - I understand that.
这名字真傻  的确有点
- Silly name. - A little bit silly.
告诉科廷州长
Huh, Tell Governor Curtin it'd be much appreciated
如果他能亲自来众议院一趟  就再好不过了
if he'd invite the House of Representatives to decide who won.
他有权这么做  也会这么做
He's entitled to do that. He'll agree to it.
然后转告那个科夫罗斯  如果他想保住席位
Then advise Coffroth, if he hopes to retain his seat,
他最好拜访一下塞德斯・史蒂文斯
that he'd better pay a visit to Thaddeus Stevens.
可怜的科夫罗斯
Oh, pity poor Coffroth!
门没锁
It opens!
你就是坎夫雷
You are Canfrey?
是科夫罗斯  史蒂文斯先生
Coffroth, Mr. Stevens,
亚历山大・科夫罗斯
Alexander Coffroth, I'm
我们是同一个州代表的吗
Are we representatives of the same state?
是  是的先生  我们中间只隔了3个位子
Y-yes sir, We sit only three desks apart.
我没见过你
I haven't noticed you. I'm
我是共和党的  你  科夫罗普  是民主党的
a Republican, and you, Coughdrop, are a Democrat?
那个
Well
我是说
Um, that is to say, I
你只不过让自己还无主见地附和
The modern travesty of Thomas Jefferson's political organization
扭曲托马斯・杰斐逊政治纲领的团体
to which you have attached yourself like a barnacle
还好意思叫自己民主党人
has the effrontery to call itself The Democratic Party.
你不过是个民主党跟屁虫
You are a Dem-O-crat.
你打算干什么  玩我吗
What's the matter with you? Are you wicked?
那个  我觉得  事实上
Well, I felt, um, formerly, I
不要紧  科夫斯诺
Never mind, Coffsnot,
你刚刚在11月的选举里被强有力的竞争对手
you were ignominiously trounced at the hustings
一个共和党人打得毫无还手之力
in November's election by your worthy challenger, a Republican.
不  先生  我没有  被打败
No, sir, I was not, um, trounced!
他想窃取我的席位  我没有输掉选举
Uh, he wants to steal my seat! I didn't lose the election
你输没输有什么区别
What difference does it make if you lost or not,
你们的州长  也是个  是个民主党人吗
the governor of our state, is A Democrat?
不  他是
No, he's a
那个  他是
A, um, a Ruh
共
Re.
和  和
- Pub. - Pub.
党  党
- Li. - Li.
人  人  共和党人
- Can. - Can. Republican.
我知道他是哪派的  我刚刚说的是个反问句
I know what he is. This is a rhetorical exercise.
那国会是被哪个党派控制的  你的吗
And Congress is controlled by what party? Yours?
你的党派被打败了
Your party was beaten,
你的敌对党现在接手了议会
your challenger's party now controls the House,
之后还会接手内务委员会
and hence the House Committee on Elections,
所以你们彻底败了
so you have been beaten.
你们马上就要卷铺盖走人  除非
You shall shortly be sent home in disgrace. Unless
我知道我要做什么  先生
I know what I must do, sir,
我会立刻加入共和党  投赞成票给
I will immediately become a Republican and vote yes for
不
NO!
科夫罗斯  会投赞成票
Coffroth will vote yes,
但是科夫罗斯会保持民主党的身份  直到投票结束
but Coffroth will remain a Democrat until after he does so.
为什么要等  我不介意现在就换
Why wait to switch? I'm happy to switch
我们想让修正案看起来是两党共同支持的  蠢货
We want to show the amendment has bipartisan support, you idiot.
等下次的议会  我让你转党派  你再换
Early in the next Congress, when I tell you to do so, you will switch parties.
现在祝贺你选举成功  你可以出去了
Now congratulations on your victory, and get out.
现在  把剩下目标的名单给我
Now give me the names of whoever else you been hunting.
乔治・伊曼  没错  伊曼
- George Yeaman. - Yes. Yeaman.
在这些人当中
Among others.
伊曼可能有戏
But Yeaman, that'd count.
YEAMAN  我知道了
- Y-E-A-M-A-N. - I got it.
我不能给修正案投赞成票
I can't vote for the amendment, Mr. Lincoln.
伊曼先生  我曾经见过一艘驳船
I saw a barge once, Mr. Yeaman,
里面全是被锁上的黑人
filled with colored men in chains,
沿密西西比河顺流而下
heading down the Mississippi
前往新奥尔良的奴隶市场
to the New Orleans slave markets.
它令我作呕
It sickened me.
不仅如此  它还给我留下阴影
And more than that, it brought a shadow down,
无法磨灭的阴影
a pall around my eyes.
从我记事起  奴隶制就一直困扰我
Slavery troubled me as long as I can remember
远远超过它对我父亲的困扰
in a way it never troubled my father,
尽管我父亲用自己的方式憎恨奴隶制
though he hated it, in his own fashion.
他知道拥有小块土地的农夫
He knew no small holding dirt farmer
无法与拥有奴隶种植园的奴隶主匹敌
could compete with slave plantations.
他带我们离开肯塔基州
He took us out from Kentucky
离开那些人  他希望在印第安纳州保持中立
to get away from them. He wanted Indiana kept free.
他不是个仁慈的人
He wasn't a kind man,
但是发自内心对公正最原始的渴求  驱使他追求自由
but there was a rough moral urge for fairness, for freedom in him.
我想这是我从他身上学到的东西
I learnt that from him, I suppose,
如果说我从他身上学到了什么的话
if little else from him.
我们从未关心过对方  伊曼先生
We didn't care for one another, Mr. Yeaman.
听到这些  我很难过  爱与仁慈
- Well, I'm sorry to hear that.- Loving kindness,
这些生活中无处不在的东西
that most ordinary thing came to me
总让我心怀感激
from other sources.. I'm grateful for that.
我  我也厌恶它  先生
I I hate it, too, sir
我恨奴隶制  但是
slavery, but
但是我们还没有为解放做好准备
but we're entirely unready for emancipation.
还有太多的问题  我们也没有为和平做好准备  不是吗
- There's too many questions - We're unready for peace too, ain't we?
当和平到来的时候
Yeah, when it comes,
我们会遇到各种棘手的难题
it'll present us with conundrums and
比我们在战争中见的 甚至比战争是更多的危险
dangers greater than any we've faced during the war,dangers greater than any
甚至是同战争时一样多的鲜血 更大的危险  同样的鲜血淋漓
we've faced during the war, bloody as it's been.bloody as it's been.
我们需要根据实际情况来尝试及调整
We'll have to extemporize and experiment with
才能找到最佳的方法和时机
what it is, when it is.
我读了你的演讲稿  乔治
I read your speech, George.
黑人和选举权  真是个难题
Negroes and the vote, that's a puzzle.
不  不  但是
No, no, but-but-but
但黑人不能  有权投票  林肯先生
but Negroes can't um vote, Mr. Lincoln.
您不会是想赋予有色人种选举权吧
You're not suggesting we enfranchise colored people.
我只是在请求你将自己
I'm asking only that you
从奴隶主势力中解放出来
disenthrall yourself from the slave powers.
我如果收到和平请愿的话会一定会告诉你
I'll let you know when there's an offer on my desk for surrender.
但现在没有
There's none before us now.
现在摆在我们面前的
What's before us now,
是第13号修正案的投票
that's the vote on the Thirteenth Amendment.
票数会咬得很紧
It's going to be so very close.
看看你能做点什么
You see what you can do.
我无法理解  他为何因此而死
I can't make sense of it, what he died for.
林肯先生  我恨他们所有人
Mr. Lincoln, I hate them all.
我恨所有黑人
I do, all black people.
我的确心存偏见
I am a prejudiced man.
我愿意改变你的偏见  但我来不是为了这个
I'd change that in you if I could, but that's not why I come.
我可能搞错了  哈顿先生
I might be wrong, Mr. Hutton,
但有色人种很可能会得到自由
but I expect colored people will most likely be free.
那时候你就会明白  是你弟弟的英勇
And when that's so, it's simple truth that your brother's
和他的牺牲  促成了这一切
bravery, and his death, helped make it so.
只有你能决定这样是不是有意义
Only you can decide whether that's sense enough for you, or not.
我对你的家人致以最深切的哀悼
My deepest sympathies to your family.
我们的人做得非常漂亮
We've managed our members to a fare-thee-well.
右翼共和党
You've had no defections
没有出现反对声音
from the Republican right to trouble you.
但你的保证呢
Whereas as to what you promised
特使团都他妈的在哪呢
where the hell are the commissioners?!
天啊  原来是真的
Oh my God It's true!
您  您骗了我  林肯先生
You you lied to me, Mr. Lincoln!
您不让我否认
You evaded my requests for a
邦联提出求和的传言
denial that-that there is a Confederate peace offer
因为确有此事
because because there is one!
我们绝对全盘皆输
We are absolutely guaranteed to lose the whole thing!
我们不需要什么该死的废奴修正案
We don't need a goddamned abolition amendment.
别揪着宪法不放了  假如  假如
- Leave the Constitution alone! - What if, what if
特使团今天出现了  或者
these peace commissioners appear today, or
或者更糟  一大早
or worse, on the morning
你可以一个州一个周的根除
State by state you can extirpate
我听不下去了
I can't listen to this anymore.
在我们把自己从奴隶制里解救出来之前
I can't accomplish a goddamned thing of any human meaning
在这场乌烟瘴气的战争结束之前
or worth until we cure ourselves of slavery,
我无法做任何对人类有价值的事情
and end this pestilential war,
不管你们或其他人是否了解
and whether any of you or anyone else knows it,
我知道我需要它
I know I need this!
这份修正案就是解救我的良药
This amendment is that cure!
现在我们走上了世界舞台  现在
We're stepped out upon the world's stage now, NOW!
人类尊严的命运掌握在我们手中
With the fate of human dignity in our hands!
多少鲜血才成就了今时今刻
Blood's been spilt to afford us this moment!
现在  现在  现在
Now now now!
可你们就知道抱怨  质问  逃避
But you grousle and heckle and dodge about
跟一群无知的坦幕尼小丑一样(坦慕尼协会  成立于1789年的纽约民主党组织  因政治腐败而臭名昭著)
like pettifogging Tammany Hall hucksters!
看看摆在你们面前的是什么
See what is before you!
睁眼看看现实  这才是最大的困难
See the here and now! That's the hardest thing,
也是唯一有意义的事情
the only thing that accounts!
通过宪法条款废除奴隶制
Abolishing slavery by constitutional provision
是一劳永逸的解决方法
settles the fate, for all coming time,
不仅解放了现今的数百万奴隶
not only of the millions now in bondage
也改变了无数子孙后代的命运
but of unborn millions to come.
再有两张选票就能实现
Two votes stand in its way,
这两张票势在必得
and these votes must be procured!
再有2张赞成票加3张弃权票  或者
We need two yeses, three abstentions, or
4张赞成加1张弃权  修正案就通过了
four yeses and one more abstention and the amendment will pass.
还有一天两夜
You got a night and a day and a night
加好几个小时的时间
and several perfectly good hours,
现在就出去拉选票
now get the hell out of here and get 'em!
好  但怎么做
Yes. But how?
拿出鹫鹰的勇气来  小子
Buzzards' guts, man.
我是美利坚合众国的总统
I am the President of the United States of America,
身披无上权力
clothed in immense power!
你们去给我把选票弄到手
You will procure me these votes.
投票当天早上  1865年1月31日
女士们先生们  欢迎来到众议院
We welcome you, ladies and gentlemen,
这对于本间民众议会厅来说是史无先例的
first in the history of this people's chamber, to your House!
阿什利先生  有请你来发言
Mr. Ashley, the floor is yours.
今天我们将对面前的这份联合决议投票
On the matter of the joint resolution before us,
本决议称为宪法第13号修正案
presenting a Thirteenth Amendment to our national Constitution,
已于去年获得参议院决议通过
which was passed last year by the Senate,
过去的几周里
and which has been debated now
在座的各位也对此进行了激烈辩论
by this estimable body for the past several weeks,
今天是投票的时刻
today we will vote.
经双方协定  我们将做简短的最终陈述
By mutual agreement, we shall hear brief final statements,
由俄亥俄州的乔治・彭德尔顿阁下开始
beginning with the honorable George Pendleton of Ohio.
我刚刚
I've just received
证实了
confirmation
之前的某个传言
of what previously has been merely rumored!
和平宣誓书
Affidavits!
忠诚的民众从里士满将它带回
From loyal citizens recently returned from Richmond.
他们证实了特使团的确已经北上
They testify that Commissioners have indeed come north
现在应该已经到达华盛顿了
and ought to have arrived by now in Washington City,
使者们此行旨在立即停止内战
bearing an offer of immediate cessation of our civil war!
是真的吗  先生
Is it true, sir?
国会大厦里有邦联使者在吗
Are there Confederate commissioners in the Capitol?
我  我不知道他们在哪  到没到
I don't I have no idea where they are or if they've arrived.
到没到
If they've arrived?!
我呼吁所有民主党同伴
I appeal to my fellow Democrats,
以及热爱和平的共和党代表
to all Republican representatives who give a fig for peace!
推迟本次投票
Postpone this vote
直到总统本人给我们一个解释为止
until we have answers from the President himself!
推迟投票  推迟投票
Postpone the vote! Postpone the vote!
先生们
Gentlemen!
我有个提议
I have made a motion!
有人愿意支持我的提议吗
Does anyone here care to second my motion?
推迟投票  推迟投票
Postpone the vote! Postpone the vote!
先生们
Gentlemen.
如果和平提议成为通过修正案的交换条件
The conservative faction of border and western Republicans
那么边境保守派和西部共和党
cannot approve this amendment,
就无法认可这份
about which we harbor grave doubts,
让我们存有重大疑问的修正案
if a peace offer is being held hostage to its success.
我决定加入民主党阵营
Joining together with our Democratic colleagues,
支持推迟投票
I second the motion to postpone.
快点  老兄  快点
Quick, man! Quick!
伍德先生想让我对这一点作出回应吗
This is precisely what Mr. Wood wishes me to respond to?
是一字不差吗  他就是想让我
Word for word, this is precisely the assurance
保证这一点吗
that he demands of me?
是的  先生
Yes, sir.
交给阿什利先生
Give this to Mr. Ashley.
我觉得  我得说  林肯先生  这
I feel, um, I have to say, Mr. Lincoln, that this
你能先出去吗
Could you please just step outside?!
你们还想聊天
You gonna have a chat now,
一屋子的众议院代表可都在等这张字条
with the whole of the House of Representatives waiting on that?
向国会做虚假陈述是会
Making false representation to Congress is
会  会被弹劾
- It's, it's - It's impeachable.
但我并没有做虚假陈述
I've made no such false representation.
但确实有
But there are!
确实有里士满来的代表团
There is a delegation from Richmond.
把字条给我  约翰尼
Give me the note, Johnnie.
请把这个交给阿什利先生
Please deliver that to Mr. Ashley.
总统手信
From the President:
据我所知  这座城市里并没有特使团
So far as I know, there are no peace commissioners in the city
之后也不可能有
nor are there likely to be.
据我所知
So far as I know?!
这根本是废话
That means nothing!
到底有没有南方来的特使团
Are there commissioners from the South or aren't there?!
总统已经答复你了  先生
The President has answered you, sir.
你的和平提议是个谎言
Your peace offer is a fiction!
这不是否认
That is not a denial.
是玩文字游戏
It is a lawyer's dodge!
哈德姆先生  你这一派满意了吗
Mr. Haddam, is your faction satisfied?
保守共和党一派满意了
The conservative Republican faction's satisfied,
我们感谢林肯先生
and we thank Mr. Lincoln.
我提议搁置伍德先生的建议
I move to table Mr. Wood's motion.
已搁置
Tabled!
科尔法议长  我要求进行主议题
Speaker Colfax, I order the main question.
现收到提议
A motion has been made
要求对第13号修正案议案进行投票
to bring the bill for the Thirteenth Amendment to a vote.
有人支持吗  我支持此提议
- Do I hear a second? - I second the motion.
提议批准  要求批准
So moved, so ordered.
书记员将
The clerk will now
请安静
Quiet please.
书记员将进行唱名投票
The clerk will now call the roll for the voting.
从康涅狄格州开始
We begin with Connecticut.
奥古斯都・本杰明先生
Mr. Augustus Benjamin,
对于此份修正案  你意见如何
on the matter of this amendment, how say you?
反对
Nay!
亚瑟・本特雷先生  反对
- Mr. Arthur Bentleigh. - Nay!
约翰・埃利斯先生  你意见如何
Mr. John Ellis, how say you?
赞成  什么
- Aye! - What?
下面是密苏里州
Missouri next.
沃尔特・埃普顿先生
Mr. Walter Appleton.
我反对
I vote no!
约西亚・波顿先生
Mr. Josiah Burton.
瘦竹竿波顿很乐意投赞成票
Beanpole Burton is pleased to vote yea!
新泽西州  尼亚麦・克莱瑞先生
The State of New Jersey. Mr. Nehemiah Cleary.
反对
No.
詹姆斯・马汀森先生
Mr. James Martinson.
马汀森委托我告诉大家
Mr. Martinson has delegated me
他身体不舒服  弃权
to say he is indisposed, and he abstains.
奥斯汀・罗伯茨先生
Mr. Austin J. Roberts.
同样不舒服  同样弃权
Also indisposed, also abstaining.
伊利诺斯州完毕
Illinois concluded.
(还差15票才能赢)
哈罗德・霍利斯特先生  你意见如何
Mr. Harold Hollister, how say you?
反对
No.
哈顿先生
Mr. Hutton?
威廉・哈顿先生  请投票
Mr. William Hutton, cast your vote.
威廉・哈顿
William Hutton,
此刻回想起死去的弟弟弗雷德里克
remembering at this moment his beloved brother Fredrick,
因此反对此项修正案
votes against the amendment.
韦伯斯特・艾伦反对
Webster Allen votes no.
韦伯斯特・艾伦  来自伊利诺伊州
Webster Allen Illinois
民主党人  投了
Democrat votes
反对
No.
哈尔伯特・洛  来自印第安纳州
Halberd Law Indiana
民主党人  反对票
Democrat votes no.
阿奇博德・莫兰
Archibald Moran
赞成
Yes.
安布罗斯・贝勒  赞成
Ambrose Bailer yes.
沃尔特・沃士本先生
Mr. Walter H. Washburn.
反对票
Votes no.
乔治・伊曼先生  你意见如何
And Mr. George Yeaman, how say you?
伊曼先生  我没听到你说的
Sorry Mr. Yeaman, I didn't hear you vote.
我说赞成  麦弗逊先生
I said aye, Mr. McPherson.
赞成  叛徒
- AAAAAYE!!! - Traitor!
叛徒  保持秩序
- Traitor! - Order!
(还差8票才能赢)
议会厅内请保持秩序
Order in that chamber!
麦弗逊先生  请继续
Mr. McPherson, you may proceed.
来自俄亥俄州的克雷・霍金斯先生
Mr. Clay R. Hawkins of Ohio.
去他的  我投赞成票
Goddamn it, I'm voting yes.
我不在乎  你来毙了我吧
I don't care. You shoot me dead!
你来毙了我吧  我投赞成票
You shoot me dead, I am voting yes!
埃德温・莱克勒克先生
Mr. Edwin F. LeClerk.
反对
No!
见鬼去吧  也来毙了我吧  赞成
Oh to hell with it, shoot me dead too. Yes!
我是说  弃权  弃权
I mean Abstention. Abstention.
亚历山大・科夫罗斯先生
Mr. Alexander Coffroth.
我投  赞成票
I Vote Yes.
赞成
Yea.
詹姆斯・布鲁克斯  反对
James Brooks Nay.
约西亚・格林奈尔  赞成
Josiah Grinnell Yea.
梅耶・施特劳斯  反对
Meyer Straus Nay.
约瑟夫・马斯特恩先生  反对
- Mr. Joseph Marstern? - Nay.
奇尔顿・埃略特先生  反对
- Mr. Chilton A. Elliot? - No!
丹尼尔・斯图尔特先生  我赞成
- Mr. Daniel G. Stuart? - I vote yes.
霍华德・盖尔福伊先生  赞成
- Mr. Howard Guilefoyle. - Yea.
约翰・麦肯兹先生  赞成
- John F. McKenzie. - Yea.
安德鲁・芬克先生  反对
- Andrew E. Fink. - Nay.
约翰・凯森先生  赞成
- Mr. John A. Kassim. - Yea.
翰瑞迪先生  反对
- Mr. Hanready. - Nay.
鲁弗斯・沃伦先生  赞成
- And Mr. Rufus Warren? - Yea.
唱名结束
The roll call concludes,
投票完毕  现在
voting is completed, now
书记员先生
Mr. Clerk.
请唱我的名字  我想投一票
Please call my name. I want to cast a vote.
我反对
I object!
议长不能投票
The Speaker doesn't vote!
议长可凭个人意愿选择投票
The Speaker may vote if he so chooses.
这种情况极其少见  先生
It is highly unusual, sir.
这个场面也不常见  彭德尔顿先生
This isn't usual, Mr. Pendleton.
这是历史性的一刻
This is history.
斯盖勒・科尔法先生意见如何
How does Mr. Schuyler Colfax vote?
当然是赞成
Aye, of course.
投票结果
The final vote.
8人缺席或弃权
eight absent or not voting,
56票反对
fifty six votes against,
119票赞成
one hundred nineteen votes for,
以两票的优势(计算方法是119-[(119+56+88)/3]*2)
with a margin of two votes
阿什利  我们做到了
Ashley, this time we've made it!
自由
freedom!
我们来自山林  我们来自平原
We will rally from the hillside, we'll gather from the plain
高喊战斗口号  誓为自由而战
Shouting the battle cry of freedom!
联邦军队万岁  战士振臂欢呼
The Union forever! Hurrah, boys, hurrah!
叛徒无处逃生  新星冉冉而升
Down with the traitor, up with the star
祝贺你  主席先生
Congratulations, Mr. Chairman.
那份议案  麦弗逊先生  我能
With the bill, Mr. McPherson, may I?
联邦军队万岁  战士振臂欢呼
The Union forever! Hurrah, boys, hurrah!
这  这可是法案原件
That's that's the official bill.
我明早归还
I'll return it in the morning.
折一下  不会弄坏
Creased but unharmed.
高喊战斗口号  誓为自由而战
Shouting the battle cry of freedom!
我们热烈响应  争做忠诚勇士
We are springing to the call of the loyal, true and brave
高喊战斗口号  誓为自由而战
Shouting the battle cry of freedom!
我们前仆后继  百万自由之身
And we'll fill our vacant ranks with a million freemen more
高喊战斗口号  誓为自由而战
Shouting the battle cry of freedom!
联邦军队万岁  战士振臂欢呼
The Union forever! Hurrah, boys, hurrah!
叛徒无处逃生  新星冉冉而升
Down with the traitor, up with the star
立于国旗之下  战士团结一心
While we rally round the flag, boys, rally once again
高喊战斗口号  誓为自由而战
Shouting the battle cry of freedom!
给你的礼物
A gift for you.
19世纪最浓墨重彩的一笔
The greatest measure of the Nineteenth Century,
虽然过程中未免有猫腻
passed by corruption,
但为全美国最高尚的人所援助并推崇
aided and abetted by the purest man in America.
真希望你当时也在场
Aah, I wish you'd been present.
我也希望  场面太壮观了
- I wish I'd been. - It was a spectacle.
你不能把女仆带进议会厅
You can't bring your housekeeper to the House.
我不会让别人说闲话  这样就足够了
I won't give them gossip. This is enough.
这样
This is
这样就太足够了
It's more than enough for now.
再给我读一遍  亲爱的
Read it to me again, my love.
兹提议
Proposed
并通过  并通过
- And adopted. - Adopted.
一份对于美国宪法的修正案
An Amendment to the Constitution of the United States.
第一条  美国境内及受其管辖之范围内
Section One: Neither slavery nor involuntary servitude,
应杜绝一切
except as a punishment for crime
奴役及非自愿劳役行为
whereof the party shall have been duly convicted,
但当其作为惩罚犯罪的措施时
shall exist within the United States,
则另当别论
or any place subject to their jurisdiction.
第二条  国会有权
- Section Two. - Congress shall have power
通过立法来保障此修正案的实施
to enforce this amendment by appropriate legislation.
大河女王号
我就有话直说了
Let me be blunt.
恢复南部各州
Will the southern states
在联邦原来的位置后
resume their former position in the Union
我们是否还来得及
speedily enough to enable us
阻止第13号修正案的通过
to block ratification of the Thirteenth Amendment?
我现在就想要和平
I'd like peace immediately.
好  然后呢
Yes, and?
我想让你们这些州
I'd like your states restored
立即回归到联邦的实际机构中
to their practical relations to the Union immediately.
如果您能以邦联的副总统的名义
If this could be given me in writing,
将此话落实到书面上
as Vice President of the Confederacy,
我会马上将此文件交给杰斐逊・戴维斯
I'd bring that document with celerity to Jefferson Davis.
先投降  然后再谈机构重组
Surrender, and we can discuss reconstruction.
除非你们书面保证
Surrender won't be thought of
我们回归之后还来得及阻止这份修正案
unless you've assured us, in writing,
否则我们不会考虑投降
that we'll be readmitted in time to block this amendment.
作为战胜方提出这样的要求未免太自大了
This is the arrogant demand of a conqueror.
你们不是战败方民众
You'll not be a conquered people,
亨特先生  你们是本国公民
you will be citizens.
重新受到宪法法律约束
Returned to the laws
并享有宪法保障的权利的公民
and the guarantees of rights of the Constitution.
宪法废除奴隶制  扼杀我们的经济(内战时期美国南部种植园经济主要依赖奴隶生产)
Which now extinguishes slavery. And with it, our economy.
国会里睚眦必报的北方佬
All our laws will be determined
将会制定我们的法律
by a Congress of vengeful Yankees.
最高法院里该死的共和党激进分子
All our rights'll be subject to a Supreme Court
将会制约我们享有的权利
benched by bloody Republican radicals.
我们的传统会毁于一旦
All our traditions will be obliterated.
我们甚至会忘记自己是谁
We won't know ourselves anymore.
我们不是来谈机构重组的
We ain't here to discuss reconstruction.
我们没有法律依据来讨论这些
We have no legal basis for that discussion.
但我不想做不公平交易
But I don't want to deal falsely.
北方各州基本都会通过第13号修正案
The Northern states'll ratify, most of 'em.
我认为
As I figure, it remains for
就算全部回归之后
two of the Southern states to do the same,
南方有两个州也会通过本案的
even after all are readmitted.
我一直在努力争取
And I been working on that.
田纳西州跟路易斯安那州
Tennessee and Louisiana.
很可能还有阿肯色州  法案会通过的
Arkansas too, most likely. It'll be ratified.
先生  奴隶制该寿终就寝了
Slavery, sir, it's done.
如果我们将自己交诸法律  亚历克斯
If we submit ourselves to law, Alex,
就算这样会使我们丧失某些自由
even submit to losing freedoms,
比如说压迫别人的自由
the freedom to oppress, for instance,
但我们会发现其它之前不曾知道的自由
we may discover other freedoms previously unknown to us.
只要你们对民主进程还抱有希望
Had you kept faith with democratic process,
不管道路多么曲折  好了  先生
- as frustrating as that can be - C'mon, sir,
至少把这点虔诚留给我们吧
spare us at least these pieties.
你是通过民主选举战胜我们的吗
Did you defeat us with ballots?
你是怎样控制联邦的
How've you held your Union together?
通过民主政治吗
Through democracy?
在你的任期里
How many hundreds of thousands
有千千万万的人丧命
have died during your administration?
先生  你的联邦建立在炮火跟牺牲之上
Your Union, sir, is bonded in cannon fire and death.
你也许是对的
It may be you're right.
但我们所做的一切都是为了向世界展示
But say all we done is show the world
民主并不是一团混乱
that democracy isn't chaos,
有一种无形的伟大力量蕴于民众团结之中
that there is a great invisible strength in a people's union?
即使承受巨大的牺牲
Say we've shown that a people can endure
我们也做到了团结一致
awful sacrifice and yet cohere?
这难道还不够挽救人们对民主的信念
Mightn't that save at least the idea of democracy to aspire to?
并最终让他们觉得民主是值得的吗
Eventually, to become worthy of?
无论如何  流血和牺牲能证明的东西
At all rates, whatever may be proven by blood and sacrifice
现在都已经证明
must've been proved by now.
我们能结束这场血战吗
Shall we stop this bleeding?
弗吉尼亚州  彼得堡市外  4月3日
投降之后  把战士们送回他们的家园
Once he surrenders, send his boys back to their homes,
他们的农场  他们的店铺
their farms, their shops.
是的  先生  像我们说定的那样
Yes sir, as we discussed.
宽大处理  不要惩罚  我不想那样
Liberality all around. No punishment. I don't want that.
领头的那些  杰夫跟其他人
And the leaders, Jeff and the rest of 'em.
就算他们趁我不留意逃到国外
If they escape, leave the country while my back's turned,
我也不会追究
that wouldn't upset me none.
和平不是表面工作
When peace comes it mustn't just be hangings.
看看你的外表
By outward appearance,
比去年老了十岁
you're ten years older than you were a year ago.
疲倦已经深入骨髓了
Some weariness has bit at my bones.
我从未想过一切会是今天看到的这样
I never seen the like of it before. What I seen today.
从未想过
Never seen the like of it before.
你一直都知道  你知道会是这样
You always knew that what this was going to be.
尸体挨着尸体  面目全非
Intimate, and ugly.
当你决定来这里的时候
You must've needed to see it close
一定是想近距离看一看吧
when you decided to come down here.
我们给了彼此机会去做可怕的事情
We've made it possible for one another to do terrible things.
并且赢了这场战争
And we've won the war.
现在你必须带领我们走出它的阴影
Now you have to lead us out of it.
阿波马托克斯郡府  弗吉尼亚州  1865年4月9日
想去旅行吗
You've an itch to travel?
挺想的
I'd like that.
坐火车去西部
To the West by rail.
我说的去国外
Overseas.
去基督圣地[指巴勒斯坦]
The Holy Land.
跟妻子在耶稣受难日
Awfully pious for a man
坐马车出来兜风  你可真虔诚
who takes his wife out buggy-riding on Good Friday.
去耶路撒冷
Jerusalem.
大卫跟所罗门走过的地方
Where David and Solomon walked.
我做梦都想踏上那座古城
I dream of walking in that ancient city.
所有人都会认为我是个疯子
All anyone will remember of me is
我毁了你的幸福
I was crazy and I ruined your happiness.
这样想的人都不了解  玛丽
Anyone thinks that doesn't understand, Mary.
当人们看着你的时候  他们会想
When they look at you, at what it cost
付出怎样的代价才能得到他拥有的一切
to live at the heart of this, they'll wonder at it.
他们会琢磨  这很正常
They'll wonder at you, they should.
但如果他们真的想知道个中滋味
But they should also look at the wretched woman by your side,
他们应该来看看你身旁这个可怜的女人
if they want to understand what this was truly like.
为了普通百姓  为了你之外的其他人
For the ordinary person. For anyone other than you.
我们要试着高兴起来
We must try to be happier.
两人都要高兴起来
We must. Both of us.
我们已经痛苦了太久了
We've been so miserable for so long.
我确实说过批准某些有色人种
I did say some colored men,
那些聪明的  受过教育的  打过仗的
the intelligent, the educated, and veterans, i qualified it.
史蒂文斯先生很愤怒
Mr. Stevens is furious.
他想知道你为什么会批准
He wants to know why you qualified it.
没人听说过什么聪明的  受过教育的
No one's heard the intelligent or the educated part.
他们听到的仅仅是
All they heard was the first time
历史上第一次有位总统提到了
any president has ever made mention
黑人选举权
of Negro voting.
我要是能说的更精彩一点就好了
Still, I wish I had mentioned it in a better speech.
史蒂文斯先生也想知道
Mr. Stevens also wants to know
您为什么没有说的更精彩一点
why you didn't make a better speech.
林肯夫人在马车上等您
Mrs. Lincoln's waiting in the carriage.
她让我提醒您注意时间  您还要去接
She wants me to remind you of the hour,  and that
哈里斯小姐跟雷斯本上校
you'll have to pick up Miss Harris and Major Rathbone.
我有麻烦了吗  没有  先生
- Am I in trouble? - No, sir.
谢谢你  斯莱德先生
Thank you, Mr. Slade.
看样子我得走了
I suppose it's time to go,
虽然我更想留下
though I would rather stay.
总统被枪杀了
The President has been shot!
总统在福特剧院被枪杀了
The President has been shot at Ford's Theater!
现在是  4月15日  周六
It's 7:22 in the morning,
早上7点22分  一切都结束了
Saturday the 15th of April. It's all over.
总统离开了人世
The President is no more.
他已经归于历史长河
Now he belongs to the ages.
我们温柔期待  我们热忱祈祷(1865年林肯第二次就职演讲)
Fondly do we hope, fervently do we pray,
但愿这名为战争的灾祸可即刻消逝
that this mighty scourge of war may speedily pass away.
然而  如果上帝要延续这苦难
Yet, if God wills that it continue
直到奴役之人数百年来
until all the wealth piled by the bondman's
以血汗堆积的财富化为乌有
two hundred and fifty years of unrequited toil shall be sunk,
直到  如数千年前之人所讲
and until every drop of blood drawn with the lash
鞭打出的血必得以刀刺出的血来偿还
shall be paid by another drawn with the sword,
直到那时  我们仍旧低吟
as was said three thousand years ago, so still it must be said
主之审判确是真实且公正的
The judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.
我们全无恶意
With malice toward none,
对所有人心怀仁爱
with charity for all,
我们坚持正义  因上帝以正义启迪我们
with firmness in the right as God gives us to see the right,
且让我们完成这未竟的事业
let us strive on to finish the work we are in,
平复这国家的创伤
to bind up the nation's wounds,
慰藉那些战争中逝去的英灵
to care for him who shall have borne the battle,
照顾烈士的遗孀及孤儿
and for his widow and his orphan,
尽一切努力
to do all which may achieve
以求在本国及世界范围内
and cherish a just and a lasting peace
保障公平正义及世代和平
among ourselves and with all nations.